<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cheap riches, or, A pocket-companion made of five hundred proverbial aphorismes &amp;c. as the next ensuinge page will more particularly notifie / by Natthanaell Church.</title>
            <author>Church, Nathanaell.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3990</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17000090</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17000090</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105695</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32912)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105695)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1611:60)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cheap riches, or, A pocket-companion made of five hundred proverbial aphorismes &amp;c. as the next ensuinge page will more particularly notifie / by Natthanaell Church.</title>
                  <author>Church, Nathanaell.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 115, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.G. to be sold at the Beare and Fountain ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Mercurius desideratus" (pp. 103-115) has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Aphorisms and apothegms.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cheap Riches,</hi> OR A Pocket-Companion, Made of Five hundred Proverbial A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſmes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the next enſuinge page will more particularly notifie.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Prov. 20 14.</bibl>
                     <p>Naught; Naught, ſaith the Buyer: but when he is gone away, then he boaſts.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Chap. 3 14.</bibl>
                     <p>For the Merchandize of it is better than the merchandize of Silver, and the Gaine thereof than fine Gold.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>By Nathanaell Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. G.</hi> to be ſold at the Beare and Fountain in <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> 1657.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:2"/>
                  <head>The Contents of the Booke.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>200 Golden ſayings by <hi>Henery Church.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>300 Silver ſayings, and the Conſcionable Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lititian, by <hi>Nathana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell Church.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:2"/>
                  <head>To the Honourable, <hi>William Pen,</hi> Vice-Admirall to the Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, whom God preſerve and proſper.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honored Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our <hi>favourable</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of <hi>tender</hi> Charity to me, have neither been <hi>few</hi> nor <hi>ſmall;</hi> the Commemoration whereof might <hi>well</hi> command your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Servant into a <hi>better</hi> and <hi>larger</hi> Teſtimony of <hi>your noble</hi> Generoſity, &amp; <hi>my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Acknowledgement. But I
<pb facs="tcp:105695:3"/> muſt act now <hi>not</hi> according <hi>to your meritorious</hi> Worth, but <hi>my ſlender</hi> Ability.</p>
                  <p>'Tis pitty that Good-Will ſhould looſe <hi>any</hi> thing, but what is <hi>not</hi> worth a Keeping: much leſſe then ſhould well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> paſſe <hi>thankleſſe</hi> on Earth, which goes not <hi>rewardleſſe</hi> in Heaven.</p>
                  <p>Sir, I cannot <hi>crowd</hi> your Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence into an Epiſtle, nor Gods <hi>miraculous</hi> Memorials into the moſt <hi>voluminous</hi> Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio.</p>
                  <p>'Tis not unknown what a
<pb facs="tcp:105695:3"/> 
                     <hi>anguiſhing</hi> Diſtemper <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted</hi> me from Country to City; <hi>baniſhed</hi> me from ſhore, and <hi>almoſt</hi> from my Self; gave me <hi>many</hi> Months Chaſe at Sea, <hi>emptied</hi> me of comfort, &amp; <hi>fill'd</hi> me with Complaints: In ſo much as a <hi>Pining</hi> Body and a <hi>repining</hi> Soule (the Lord forgive me) were mine <hi>inſeparable</hi> Companions for a <hi>long</hi> time. But I will be <hi>diſcontented</hi> at nothing but my <hi>own</hi> Diſcontent.</p>
                  <p>Ever ſince I was your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours <hi>Weak</hi> and <hi>Worthleſſe</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:105695:4"/> Chaplain in the <hi>Lyon, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion, Fairfax, Triumph,</hi> and the <hi>James,</hi> I wanted <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> but Thankefulneſs; nor could I complain of <hi>any</hi> thing but my <hi>own</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliefe. <hi>I was among you in fear, &amp; weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and much trembling,</hi> that I may borrow <hi>Pauls</hi> words 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.3. though I cannot utter them in that <hi>more ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> ſenſe, that <hi>He</hi> doth.</p>
                  <p>But I may well ſing to God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1,2,3,4,5. <hi>verſes,</hi> and I pray God make my Life (which he hath <hi>graciouſly</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:105695:4"/> lengthned) a Comment upon the <hi>whole</hi> Pſalm.</p>
                  <p>When I think of my Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratives for Soul and Bodie, that Counſell, Encouragement and Comfort, which your <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> Head, your <hi>tender</hi> Eye, your <hi>honeſt</hi> heart, your <hi>libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> Hand, your <hi>faithfull</hi> Tongue adminiſtred unto me, I ſay (from the ſoul of a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanael</hi>) For my Life I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not thanke you <hi>too much,</hi> nor GOD <hi>enough</hi> And indeed, while I am telling you ſtories of your own Kind-heartedneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:105695:5"/> me-thinks I heare you reply on this poor <hi>crooked</hi> Stoper, <hi>look up</hi> higher <hi>to the LIVING GOD,</hi> &amp; ſay to that the ſame <hi>CELESTIAL EXCEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENTISSIMO, What ſhall I</hi> do <hi>unto thee, O thou preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of men!</hi> Job 7.20. <hi>What ſhal I render to the Lord for</hi> All <hi>his benefits towards me?</hi> Pſ. 116.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. I have tryed <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> helps for my Recovery, but all to <hi>no</hi> purpoſe. Now I feel, and <hi>find</hi> that <hi>the Lords way is in the Sea, and his Path in the</hi> mighty <hi>waters, and his
<pb facs="tcp:105695:5"/> foote-ſteps are</hi> not <hi>knowne,</hi> Pſal. 77.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. To this <hi>good</hi> and <hi>great</hi> God (from whoſe Ocean you borrow your ſtreams of Bounty) I recommend your <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>all yours,</hi> both by Sea and Land, <hi>humbly</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring him to <hi>bind up</hi> your Soul in the <hi>Bundle of Life,</hi> to let the <hi>Bleſſing of Him that was</hi> ready <hi>to</hi> periſh come upon you (as <hi>Job</hi> 9.3.) The LORD Regiſter you into the Number of thoſe whoſe Bowels <hi>yearn</hi> to the <hi>diſtreſſed,</hi> wh ſe Hands <hi>open</hi> to the <hi>Afflicted,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:105695:6"/> and whom None is <hi>able</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but He, who <hi>hath Moſt</hi> and <hi>deſerves All,</hi> yet is <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented</hi> with a <hi>little</hi> in ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; in whom I reſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours <hi>often</hi> engaged And <hi>still</hi> indebted, <hi>Nathanael Church.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:6"/>
                  <head>Prevention to the Reader.</head>
                  <p>FRiends, doe not thinke that theſe <hi>brief</hi> Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were drawn out of <hi>thoſe</hi> Texts of Scripture quoted <hi>after</hi> them. For the Sayings were written <hi>ſome</hi> Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>any</hi> Quotations were made. And thoſe places of Scripture were <hi>only</hi> ſet down to ſhew how <hi>near</hi> theſe <hi>rationall</hi> Maximes come to <hi>divine</hi> Verity, and how nigh Kin Faith and Reaſon are.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:7"/>
                  <p>I Call my Fathers <hi>Golden ſayings,</hi> and my own <hi>Silver,</hi> becauſe his have the Prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>not only</hi> of Time, <hi>but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo</hi> of Eſtimate: and beſides <hi>mine</hi> Excell <hi>his</hi> in Nothing but Number, as Children do the Parents, and as Stars do the Sun and Moon.</p>
                  <p>As for my <hi>own</hi> Sentences, they have little or nothing in them that I have <hi>begg'd,</hi> or <hi>borrowed.</hi> Nay I fear, it will be ſaid, that they have <hi>too much</hi> of my Self in them. But though they are like the
<pb facs="tcp:105695:7"/> Cobweb, ſpun out of my <hi>own</hi> Bowels, yet <hi>ſome</hi> of them <hi>well applyed</hi> may ſtench a <hi>bleeding</hi> Conſcience.</p>
                  <p>They are (moſt of them) <hi>common</hi> Notions, but <hi>never</hi> the <hi>worſe</hi> for that: For the Sun, the Day, the Ayre, the Fire, the Water, the Earth, and the Goſpel are not the <hi>worſe</hi> for being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, but the <hi>better. Boni proprium eſt eſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune,</hi> Tis <hi>proper</hi> to that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is good, to be <hi>common:</hi> And that which does good to <hi>many,</hi> is <hi>more excell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:105695:8"/> and <hi>more divine,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as <hi>Ariſtot.</hi>) then that, that does good to <hi>one</hi> only.</p>
                  <p>They are Trilineals, or <hi>three lines</hi> a piece (moſt of them) and ſo more <hi>portable</hi> for the Memory.</p>
                  <p>They are Pentad's, or juſt <hi>five</hi> in a Page: ſo that a man, (though <hi>ſtreightned</hi> in Time, notwithſtanding) may read to a Period <hi>preſently,</hi> &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a <hi>Theam to think on</hi> with him, as an Antidote againſt <hi>worſe</hi> thoughts.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:8"/>
                  <p>The very <hi>blank</hi> Spaces <hi>between</hi> them will prove <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious</hi> to one that has <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> Good-husbandry, for there he may <hi>interſcribe</hi> any <hi>other</hi> compendious Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegme, at Pleaſure and Leiſure.</p>
                  <p>As for my failings, I hope they will prove either but <hi>ordinary,</hi> or but <hi>few.</hi> But I could wiſh this were the <hi>worst</hi> uſe I had made of my Pen, I hope 'tis <hi>not</hi> the <hi>beſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:9"/>
                  <l>And he that every day doth mend,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſure be perfect in the end</l>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Much good</hi> may they do thee, <hi>Who ever</hi> thou art, Friend or Foe: ſo ſaies He, who is (in his Prayers to God for thee,)</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine, (whether thou wilt or no) <hi>N. C.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomia">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:9"/>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <head>To the Reader.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>READER,</hi> Th' haſt here a <hi>little Cabinet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Jewels rare:</hi> a <hi>precious Ring</hi> be ſet</l>
                     <l>With <hi>richeſt Stones:</hi> a <hi>Noſe-gay</hi> that doth yeeld</l>
                     <l>A <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>fragrant</hi> Smell. Each <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> Field</l>
                     <l>Hath not ſuch <hi>Flowers</hi> as theſe. To tell thee true,</l>
                     <l>Here's <hi>nothing</hi> doth accoſt thee, but whats new.</l>
                     <l>Theſe are not <hi>Forreign Proverbs Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> ſure: they are all <hi>Brittains born and breed.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>READER,</hi> thoul't ſay, having read th' <hi>Adages</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Author's <hi>MASTER OF THE SENTENCES.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Edw: Hicks</hi> M.A. utriuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Academiae.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <pb facs="tcp:105695:10"/>
                     <head>To the Reader.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>REeader,</hi> Th'haſt here a birth, which as I gather,</l>
                     <l>For it's conception ows to <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Father:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>An Iſſue which for'ts Mid wifery doth ſtand</l>
                     <l>Mixtly indebted both to Sea and Land.</l>
                     <l>A <hi>lawful Prize.</hi> But o the Devil of Gain!</l>
                     <l>One <hi>Pocket</hi> now <hi>two</hi> Churches can contain!</l>
                     <l>Well. Yet beware thou, how thy Cenſure blots</l>
                     <l>The Author: ther's no Church without its ſpots.</l>
                     <l>He's a <hi>Nathanael,</hi> credit me, and I'le</l>
                     <l>Avouch, when he wrote theſe, there was <hi>no guile.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Poſſeſt his heart. Come, ſhew thy ſelf to be</l>
                     <l>A Friend to Church, and I'le be ſo to thee.</l>
                     <l>But if thou haſt a place for wonder fit,</l>
                     <l>Give it the <hi>CHURCH and COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON WEALTH of WIT.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>C. F.</hi> M.A.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <pb facs="tcp:105695:10"/>
                     <head>Authoris Amicus ad Lecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>MUch</hi> Profit, Wiſdome, Learning, in <hi>Few</hi> Words,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Small,</hi> this <hi>Cheap,</hi> this <hi>Uſefull</hi> Tract affords.</l>
                     <l>On any Page vouchſafe to caſt thine Eye:</l>
                     <l>And if thou canſt not <hi>like</hi> it, caſt it by.</l>
                     <l>How e're <hi>deſpiſe</hi> not this <hi>Sententi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> Schoole;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Leaſt thou be ſentenc'd a <hi>Cenſorious Foole.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reader</hi> what-ever, if thou <hi>honeſt be:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It merits to <hi>keep Company</hi> with thee.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Will. Bodham.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <pb facs="tcp:105695:11"/>
                     <head>To his Ingenous Friend <hi>Mr. Nathanael Church</hi> on his <hi>Pocket-Companion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>VVHil'ſt thou was toſs't upon the waving Main,</l>
                     <l>Me-thought <hi>Noes Ark was floating</hi> once again.</l>
                     <l>Thy Friends on Land were troubled much for thee,</l>
                     <l>To prove their <hi>Churches viſibility.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now if I want thy <hi>good ſociety,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy book mean while ſhall my <hi>Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> be.</l>
                     <l>Where whiles thy Hand ſpeaks to mine Eye: ſo here.</l>
                     <l>Mine eye becomes thy Hands Interpreter.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:105695:11"/>
                     <l>If <hi>great Bookes</hi> be <hi>great evils,</hi> thou ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wn</l>
                     <l>A remedy: Thine's but a <hi>little one.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Since <hi>Coyn's</hi> grown ſcant, 'twas wiſely done by thee,</l>
                     <l>To keep our <hi>Pockets</hi> from <hi>vacuity.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Tho. Ford.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <pb facs="tcp:105695:12"/>
                     <head>Author ad Patrem jam 17. annos defunctum.</head>
                     <l>WEll, I'le drop one Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticke, rather</l>
                     <l>Then by a Clowniſh ſilence robb my Father.</l>
                     <l>Leſt. if by me that name be vilifi'd,</l>
                     <l>I'me named ſacriligious parricide,</l>
                     <l>Though Him to praiſe, there needs no Paines, or Skill.</l>
                     <l>Of whom his very Foes could not ſpeake ill.</l>
                     <l>Here needs no Floriſhes, go, cunning Pates,</l>
                     <l>Goe, ſleep: His own workes praiſe him in the Gates.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:105695:12"/>
                     <l>Nay all the Rhetorick I can deviſe,</l>
                     <l>Is but to multiply Tautologies.</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Theologick Miſcellanies can</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Him ſtudious prove, to know both GOD and MAN.</l>
                     <l>His Coffer long agoe is dead and rotten:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Good mans Treaſure</hi> muſt not be forgotten.</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Chriſtian letters</hi> moſt elebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,</l>
                     <l>Now out of print, I'de buy at any Rate.</l>
                     <l>Meane while I will be thankefull, not repine,</l>
                     <l>My Fathers Gold and Silver both are <hi>Mine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>N. C.</signed>
                     </closer>
                     <trailer>
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> H. C. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="compendium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:13"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105695:13"/>
                  <head>A Pocket-cOmpanion.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>1.</label> 
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hings <hi>unkown</hi> we neither <hi>deſire,</hi> nor <hi>feare</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>2.</label> 'Tis extraordinary Wickedneſs, to think Nothing to be <hi>wicked.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>3.</label> Some Hearers are like the Aire, only hot, when the Sun <hi>ſhineth.</hi> See <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. four ſorts of hearers.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>4.</label> 
                           <hi>Short</hi> Time hath <hi>long</hi> Wings, and flies away <hi>ſwiftly.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>5.</label> We may <hi>well</hi> ſpare our Thoughts from things <hi>impoſſible</hi> and <hi>unprofitable.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105695:14"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>6.</label> That Soul that is <hi>moſt watchfull,</hi> it <hi>leaſt ſinfull,</hi> Matth. 26.41. Rev. 16.15.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>7.</label> We can fathom from a Giants <hi>Heart</hi> to his <hi>Mouth;</hi> not a Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers, ſee <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>8.</label> 
                           <hi>Gods Mercies</hi> are as the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, not as the Land-flood, <hi>viz. conſtant,</hi> not <hi>uncertain,</hi> and <hi>beneficiall</hi> not <hi>prejudiciall.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>9.</label> 
                           <hi>Milk not drawn,</hi> putrifies; <hi>Riches not uſed,</hi> ruſt. See <hi>James</hi> 5.2,3. ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.19,20.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>10.</label> We are like the Aire, <hi>dark</hi> of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> Grace make us <hi>light,</hi> ſee 2 Cor. 4 6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105695:14"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>11.</label> 
                           <hi>Prophane</hi> Teachers like <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curiall ſtatues,</hi> direct Others, not Themſelves, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. v. 1. and v. 17. to 24.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>12.</label> This <hi>little</hi> Time is between too <hi>vaſt</hi> Eternities, conſider <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.24. to the end.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>13.</label> If two <hi>whiſtle,</hi> the Dog ſtill comes to Him that hath the <hi>Bone, note</hi> Sauls <hi>words,</hi> 1 Sam. 22.7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>14.</label> The Hawke flies <hi>higheſt,</hi> but the <hi>Hen</hi> is the <hi>better diſh,</hi> ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.33. Taſt the next <hi>Aphoriſm.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>15.</label> The Wicked have often the <hi>greateſt preferment,</hi> but the Godly are alwaies <hi>moſt profitable,</hi> Heſt. 6. and 7. Chapters.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105695:15"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>16.</label> The ſhadow of Fame is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times long, ſometimes ſhort. As in <hi>Joſeph, Job, Jacob, Nebnehadnezer,</hi> Dan. 4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>17.</label> Much Grace makes a little Heaven here: truth of Grace makes ſure of Heaven hereafter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>18.</label> A Diſpenſation <hi>to</hi> ſin is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo good as a Diſpoſition <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> ſin. Compare <hi>Saul</hi> with <hi>Paul.</hi> Study <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. to the end.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>19.</label> The more the Church ſuffers <hi>here,</hi> the Enemy ſhall ſuffer <hi>hereafter, Micah.</hi> 7,8,9,10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.15.16,17,18.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>20.</label> 
                           <hi>Cham</hi> eſcaped drowing by Water, yet was drowned in ſin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.18. to 28.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105695:15"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>21.</label> Diſtempered Affections make our Griefs exceed our Croſſes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.1. <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Jonah.</hi> 4.9.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>22.</label> That which is a Burthen <hi>within,</hi> is like to be a Blemiſh <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> Pſalm 38.4,11. Rom. 6.21.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>23.</label> Sin often prevailes againſt the godly, but their Reſolution ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 39.1. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 17.3.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>24.</label> Heavines and Fear very much hinder <hi>good duties,</hi> Pſalm 69 3. Prov. 29.25. 1 Sam. 26.19. Pſalm 40.12.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="25" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>25.</label> In out diſtempers, or ill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, or ſolitarineſs, Sathan watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; ſee <hi>Aphoriſm</hi> 278.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="26" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105695:16"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>26.</label> 
                           <hi>Diabolicall thoughts</hi> are as <hi>duſt blowne;</hi> the fault is not in the <hi>Eyes,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.7,8,9. Rom. 7.17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="27" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>27.</label> What Satan <hi>ſuggeſts</hi> that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly <hi>keepes.</hi> As in the deſpaire of <hi>Cain, Saul, Judas,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="28" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>28.</label> They <hi>never proſper,</hi> whom Gods Children do <hi>pray againſt,</hi> Exo. 17.11. Iſa. 54.17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="29" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>29.</label> 
                           <hi>GOD</hi> waſhes with <hi>blood,</hi> We with <hi>teares,</hi> Luke 7.38. Revel. 1.5. Zach. 13.1.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="30" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>30.</label> None do believe, becauſe they are <hi>worthy</hi> to believe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="31" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105695:16"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>31.</label> 'Tis better to <hi>beare</hi> Scoffes, than to <hi>diſſemble</hi> Holineſs, <hi>Marke</hi> 8.38. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Jer:</hi> 20.7,8,9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.36.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="32" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>32.</label> We have more comfort of what we <hi>give,</hi> than of what we <hi>get,</hi> Pſal. 39.6. Eccleſ. 2.18,19. Pſalm 41.1,2,3,4. Acts 20.35.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="33" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>33.</label> Men are aſhamed to make <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction,</hi> who ſhamed not to <hi>ſin,</hi> Job. 31.33. 1 Sam. 15.9,11,15,30.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="34" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>34.</label> A <hi>true Convert</hi> purſueth Sin to <hi>Victory,</hi> 2. Tim. 4.7. Rom. 12.21. 1 John 5.4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="35" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>35.</label> The World is <hi>unſtable,</hi> being <hi>round;</hi> the New-Jeruſalem is <hi>firme,</hi> being <hi>foure-ſquare,</hi> Revel. 21.16. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="36" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105695:17"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>36.</label> We call that chance (or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance) which comes between the Purpoſe and the End.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="37" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>37.</label> We are <hi>ſecure</hi> amongſt Friends, But <hi>watchfull</hi> amongſt Enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Neh.</hi> 7.3.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="38" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>38.</label> Breath is not the life, yet we live with it: workes ſave not, yet we are ſaved with them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="39" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>39.</label> 
                           <hi>Chriſt</hi> obeyed for ſatisfaction, <hi>we</hi> obey for Gratulation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5 18.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="40" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>40.</label> Our waies are direct and ſtreight, when both Ends agree with the Middle.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="41" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105695:17"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>41.</label> There is a thirſt of Emptineſſe, and another of Deſire: the firſt Gods people have no more but in <hi>this</hi> life.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="42" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>42.</label> Secret ſins are ſeeds that will ſprout, if they be not <hi>timely</hi> nipt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12,13. See <hi>Aph.</hi> 281.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="43" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>43.</label> To look to our ſelves, AND to our Enemies, is the only way to be ſafe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="44" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>44.</label> A well-contented low eſtate is the beſt Preferment. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.33. and <hi>Chapter</hi> 30 7,8,9.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="45" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>45.</label> A <hi>large</hi> Conſcience all the life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ime, will prove an <hi>heavy</hi> Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nce on the death-bed.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="46" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105695:18"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>46.</label> Condemn not in <hi>Generall</hi> for <hi>one</hi> fault, nor yet juſtifie the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</hi> Prov. 24.16. Matth. 18,15,16,17. Levit. 19.17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="47" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>47.</label> We are commanded to <hi>take up</hi> the Croſſe, not by baſe courſes to <hi>ſhun</hi> it, <hi>Math.</hi> 16.24.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="48" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>48.</label> A man by <hi>wiſedome gets</hi> an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, but cannot <hi>leave wiſedome with</hi> his Eſtate, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.18.19.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="49" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>49.</label> If God break our <hi>Ships,</hi> and give us <hi>boards,</hi> we may <hi>ſwim</hi> to <hi>ſhoare,</hi> Acts 24.47. ſee Job 1.21. and Chap. 42.11.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="50" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>50.</label> The <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>wicked</hi> is Hell; not the end of their <hi>aime,</hi> but of their <hi>courſe,</hi> Prov. 14,12. and 16,25.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="51" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105695:18"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>51.</label> Every Luſt <hi>ſtreigthens</hi> us, the <hi>removall</hi> gives us <hi>liberty.</hi> Rom. 6.12.14,16 and Chap. 8 2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="52" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>52.</label> Thoſe which be <hi>ever drinking</hi> without Thirſt, ſhall <hi>ever thirſt</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Drinking, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.11. to the 15.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="53" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>53.</label> 
                           <hi>GOD</hi> judges certainly <hi>a prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> Man charitably <hi>a poſteriore,</hi> Prov. 16.1,2. Pſal. 139, all 2 Sam. 12.18. and 1 Kings 3.26,27.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="54" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>54.</label> We may be <hi>weake</hi> &amp; <hi>wiſe</hi> both at <hi>once,</hi> as the Coney, the Piſmire, and Chicken, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.18. Prov.6.6,7,8. Ch. 30.25,26. Reade and do Matth. 23.37.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="55" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>55.</label> The <hi>wicked</hi> are like a <hi>wheele, unſtable, creaking,</hi> and at laſt <hi>burned,</hi> Pſal. 83.13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="56" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105695:19"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>56.</label> Beaſts have a bodily preſence to <hi>eate:</hi> Chriſtians to <hi>edefie,</hi> Pſal. 104.14 28. Pſal. 145.15,16. Col. 4.6, 1 Tim. 1.4. Eph. 4.29 30.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="57" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>57.</label> Chriſt <hi>refuſed</hi> the Worlds Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, and then Angels came unto him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4 8,9,10,11.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="58" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>58.</label> The more we <hi>ſubdue</hi> the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites,</hi> out luſts, the more we <hi>enjoy Canaan</hi> our reſt, ſee <hi>Judg.</hi> 2.22,23. and ſo of the <hi>Gibeonites, Joſh.</hi> 9.27.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="59" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>59.</label> The deceitfull Tradeſ-man workes on the ignorance or Need of the Buyer, <hi>Docet experientia rerum,</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="60" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>60.</label> To do good to the godly (and (and ungodly) is not only a Curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, but a bounded Duty, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.44. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. End ſo.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="61" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105695:19"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>61.</label> In things <hi>indifferent</hi> (or <hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>) we are to look what is <hi>meet</hi> to be done, and then to <hi>doe</hi> it</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="62" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>62.</label> Thoſe Gifts do <hi>bind</hi> us moſt, that come from a <hi>free</hi> Giver, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.7,8,12.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="63" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>63.</label> If Injuries be our Enemies, let Forgiveneſſe be our Weapon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.14,15.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="64" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>64.</label> It is well, when the End of our Paſſion is the Beginning of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, 2 Kings 5.11,12,13,14. <hi>Naamans</hi> caſe, and <hi>Peters,</hi> Mark 14.71,72.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="65" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>65.</label> The Favours that Forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth <hi>hide,</hi> Thankfulneſſe layes <hi>open</hi> to Review, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.2,34,5,6,7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="66" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105695:20"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>66.</label> Violent Affections to <hi>Gaine,</hi> bring violent Afflictions at the <hi>loſſe.</hi> See <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.22. <hi>James</hi> 5.1,2,3,4,5. <hi>Prov.</hi> 38. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9,10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="67" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>67.</label> Hell tormeneth only the <hi>bad,</hi> the Uſurer torments the <hi>good,</hi> Rev. 21.8. and Chap. 22.15. Pſalm 15.5. Neh. 5.9 10. ſee Prov. 28.8. Read <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 8.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="68" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>68.</label> An <hi>ill-favoured</hi> Snake is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Companion than a <hi>well-favoured</hi> Harlot, <hi>For an Harlot is the Eve of a Serpent.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="69" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>69</label> 'Tis not comely to ſtep from the Cradle of <hi>ignorance</hi> to the Chaire of <hi>cenſure, Job</hi> 32.6,7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="70" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>70.</label> Tis better to be <hi>uncomfortably</hi> conſcionable, than <hi>unconſcionably comfortable,</hi> Pſal. 37.16. Prov. 15.15,16,17. Chap. 16.8.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="71" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105695:20"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>71.</label> We ſhould pray that Miniſters may have <hi>life</hi> in their Doctrine, and Doctrine in their <hi>life, Epheſ.</hi> 6.18 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2,4,5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. to the 8. verſ.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="72" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>72.</label> The Hand by feeding the <hi>Body</hi> gives nouriſhment unto it <hi>ſelf.</hi> 1 Cor. 12.14. to 27. verſe, Epeſ. 4 28. and Aph. 438.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="73" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>73.</label> 'Tis an happy Wed lock to marry in <hi>Diſpoſitions,</hi> as well as in <hi>Bodies,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="74" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>74.</label> Our corrupt nature deſires not ſo much <hi>good</hi> things, as <hi>new</hi> things <hi>Athenean like,</hi> Acts 17.19. to 22.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="75" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>75.</label> 
                           <hi>GOD</hi> layes the Reines on Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <hi>necke,</hi> but pulls not the Bit out of her <hi>mouth,</hi> Eccleſ. 1,2,3,11,12. compared, with <hi>verſe</hi> 1.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="76" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:105695:21"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>76.</label> We read often that the Devill is a Lyar, but ſeldome that he is a Swearer. <hi>We are too apt to beleeve the Devil will out an Oath,</hi> ſaies one.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="77" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>77.</label> We ſhould alway ſet God before us, and our ſelves alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: ſee <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 16.8. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139 all. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.15.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="78" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>78.</label> 'Tis an <hi>heavy</hi> loſs to loſe our Prayers, either the Act, or Event, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Pſal</hi> 109.7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="79" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>79.</label> God will not in trouble ſhelter the prophane man under his wings, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 32.6,7,10,11.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="80" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>80.</label> The falls of Profeſſors bring <hi>griefe</hi> to the godly, and <hi>ſcorne</hi> to the wicked, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.21.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="81" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:105695:21"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>81.</label> In Slaunders we ſhould be moved more for the <hi>ſin</hi> againſt God, then for our own <hi>hurt,</hi> and ſo in all other miſchiefs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="82" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>82.</label> Gods Favour makes us ſet light by the worlds Frowns, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.28. <hi>John</hi> 16.33.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="83" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>83.</label> 'Tis devilliſh to be evill in good company; 'tis gracious to be good in evill company, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.10. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7,8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="84" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>84.</label> An humble heart &amp; contempt of the world are hardly gotten in Proſperity, <hi>Job</hi> 21.7. to 16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.32</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="85" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>85.</label> A feigned Obedience in Life, brings but a feigned Comfort in Death, <hi>Job</hi> 8.13. and Chap. 20.5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="86" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:105695:22"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>86.</label> Thoſe which can be <hi>content</hi> to be wicked, ſhall to their Diſcontent be <hi>counted</hi> wicked, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.12.14.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="87" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>87.</label> Men may <hi>ſin</hi> in Jeſt, yet at laſt be <hi>puniſhed</hi> in Earneſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.23. Chap. 26.18,19. with Chap. 16.25.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="88" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>88.</label> We ſhould never forget Gods <hi>Water-workes</hi> in 88. nor the Devils <hi>Fire-workes,</hi> Nov. 5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="89" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>89.</label> He that <hi>willingly defames</hi> me, <hi>unwillingly adds</hi> to my Reward, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.11,12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="90" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>90.</label> The Crane winds up <hi>heavy</hi> things; the Power of <hi>GOD</hi> raiſes up <hi>groſſe</hi> ſinners, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. all.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="91" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105695:22"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>91.</label> Our Wives may be <hi>leſſe faire</hi> or <hi>Witty</hi> than others: yet we love them better, becauſe they are our own.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="92" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>92.</label> A <hi>curſed</hi> perſon uſing a <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> meanes; cannot <hi>alwaies</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, As in <hi>Haman, Saul, Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phell.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="93" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>93.</label> Our wealth is but a <hi>paſſe,</hi> to keep us from <hi>begging</hi> (vagrant-like) in our journey, ſee <hi>Gen</hi> 28.20, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="94" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>94.</label> The laſt end of our <hi>thoughts</hi> ſhould be thoughts of our <hi>laſt end,</hi> Deut. 32.29. Pſalm. 394.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="95" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>95.</label> 'Tis better <hi>humbly</hi> to <hi>confeſſe Evills,</hi> than <hi>proudly</hi> to <hi>boaſt</hi> of our <hi>Goodneſſ,</hi> Math. 23.12. Luke 18.10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o 14.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="96" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105695:23"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>96.</label> What the broken heart ſeekes that the mercifull heart findes, and that is Mercy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.1.17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 57.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="97" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>97.</label> When God is our object, then the world is our abject, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.15,16,17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="98" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>98.</label> Sinfull pleaſures will come to nothing, whether they have a being or not See <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="99" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>99.</label> There is more pleaſure to <hi>ſubdue</hi> our luſts, than to <hi>fulfill</hi> them. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1,2,7,8.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="100" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>100.</label> Thoſe that ſpeak ſo much of Luck and Fortune, have not been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in Gods providence.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="101" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105695:23"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>101.</label> We obſerve Injuries, let us obſerve our ſelves how we beare the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ame, Prov. 16.32. Chap. 24.29. Ro. 12.18, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="102" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>102.</label> I will look on others Vertues, when I the more hate mine own Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2,3,4. 1 Pet. 3,3,4,5,6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="103" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>103.</label> An heart full of Goodneſſe is worth many heads full of knowledge 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. all. <hi>Iames</hi> 4.17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="104" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>104.</label> The <hi>being</hi> of ſin in us brings Death, the <hi>reigning</hi> of ſin in us brings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he ſecond death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12,21.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="105" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>105.</label> I like that Policy, that ſtudies more to grow <hi>good</hi> than great. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.23. <hi>Ier.</hi> 45.5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="106" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:105695:24"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>106.</label> I am miſerable <hi>without</hi> a Friend, and know not my Friend without <hi>miſery,</hi> Job 16.2. Prov. 17.17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="107" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>107.</label> 
                           <hi>Wicked men</hi> are ſo <hi>preſerve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> from <hi>Evils,</hi> as they are <hi>reſerved</hi> for <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,</hi> Jer. 12.1,2,3. Job 21.30.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="108" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>108.</label> Firſt, let us make <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and then let us make <hi>Prayers,</hi> Pſalm. 66.18. Iob 11.13,14,15.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="109" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>109.</label> The <hi>deſire</hi> of Grace, is <hi>Grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> to deſire; ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.8,9.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="110" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>110.</label> Bad Company, that have n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> grace, hurts the <hi>good,</hi> that have <hi>ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> corruption to work unpon.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="111" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:105695:24"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>111.</label> To do <hi>no</hi> good workes; or elſe to <hi>truſt</hi> in workes done, are our Rocks to ſplit us: See <hi>Aporiſme</hi> 293.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="112" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>112.</label> Becauſe our Life is ſo <hi>miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> tis a comfort we are <hi>mortal.</hi> ſee Job 14.1. Gen. 47.9.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="113" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>113.</label> If Matrimony be a <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>money,</hi> the Concluſion is, the <hi>Iſſue</hi> may be <hi>naught,</hi> ſee 1 Tim. 6.9,10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="114" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>114.</label> ALL the ſorrow of a <hi>godly man</hi> is not <hi>godly ſorrow,</hi> As in <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 37.35. and <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 18. 33. but compared with Chap. 19. the 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>irſt Verſes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="115" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>115.</label> Our <hi>indiſpoſition</hi> ſhould trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us as much as our ill <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> Prov. 7.19. to the 25.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="116" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105695:25"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>116.</label> The Stars appeare not in the Day; and Patience is not ſeen in Proſperity, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.3. Chap. 12.12. with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.6. and <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.14.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="117" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>117.</label> The End is <hi>firſt</hi> in Intention, and <hi>laſt</hi> in Execution, <hi>Ariſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="118" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>118.</label> 
                           <hi>Young</hi> Controverſers like chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren turn to the <hi>end</hi> of their Book, not having learnt the <hi>beginning,</hi> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="119" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>119.</label> 'Tis madneſſe to practice firſt and then take advice, ſee <hi>Eccleſ. Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> 5. the 7. firſt Verſes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.25.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="120" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>120.</label> If Gods Word be our <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſellor</hi> all day, it will be our <hi>Comfort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> at night, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 1.2. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 24.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="121" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105695:25"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>121.</label> Our times have more liberty for Conference then <hi>moſt</hi> of us do make <hi>uſe</hi> of, ſee <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 116,7. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9 12.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="122" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>122.</label> 
                           <hi>God</hi> hears our prayer accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our <hi>good,</hi> not our <hi>Wills,</hi> Pſal. 34.10. <hi>James</hi> 43. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.14.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="123" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>123.</label> Our Care cannot <hi>alter</hi> things, let our Patience <hi>bear</hi> them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.1 to Verſe 8.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="124" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>124.</label> 'Tis beter to have our Minds fitted to our <hi>Eſtates,</hi> then our <hi>Eſtates</hi> to our Minds Read. Mr. <hi>Burroughes Jewel,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Watſons Charter.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="125" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>125.</label> A man of <hi>ſolid</hi> Underſtanding prefers an <hi>inch</hi> of Profit before an <hi>ell</hi> of Pleaſure. <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 44.9. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.1, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="126" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:105695:26"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>126.</label> Thoſe that <hi>know much,</hi> may miſs of Holineſs: thoſe that ſtrive to <hi>Obey,</hi> ſhall not miſs of Happineſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="127" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>127.</label> The Aggravation of a <hi>great</hi> ſin, is not the Approbation of a <hi>ſmall</hi> one, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.47,48.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="128" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>128.</label> Much Hearing makes a <hi>learned</hi> Head: much Prayer makes a <hi>gracious</hi> Heart, ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3.6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="129" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>129</label> 
                           <hi>Falſe</hi> Friends may prove <hi>true</hi> Enemies, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.18. <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.5,6. and Chap. 28.23. and Chap. 23.6,7,8.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="130" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>130.</label> My Conſcience hath to doe with my <hi>Sin before</hi> Commiſſion, with my <hi>Perſon after</hi> Commiſſion.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="131" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:105695:26"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>131.</label> Wicked men be <hi>Fooles:</hi> were they <hi>wiſe,</hi> they would endeavour to be <hi>godly-wiſe,</hi> Rom. 1.22. Chap. 1.16.9.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="132" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>132.</label> Earth is the place, where many <hi>enjoy</hi> and yet <hi>looſe</hi> Happineſs. <hi>Job</hi> 20.5,15. <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.7. to the 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.35,36. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.12.19.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="133" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>133.</label> My Prayers make me <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>reverence</hi> God, and the Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>endures</hi> afterward.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="134" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>134.</label> The Sunne <hi>ſtood ſtill</hi> for <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> whereas Covetouſneſſe was buſie in <hi>Achan,</hi> Joſh. 7.21. Chap., 10.13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="135" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>135.</label> Our life is as a Day; the Night is Death; our Beds are as our Graves; our Ariſing is as the Reſurrection.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="136" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:105695:27"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>136.</label> We ſhould not raſhly run into <hi>ſecret</hi> things, nor let ſlip <hi>known</hi> truths: ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="137" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>137.</label> The Birth of the <hi>Brain</hi> is ſtriven for more than the Birth of the <hi>Body.</hi> Read and Ponder <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.12.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="138" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>138.</label> Their waies are <hi>ſinfull,</hi> that were a Mantle of <hi>non-imployment,</hi> Matth. 26.7. ſee Chap. 25.24. to 31. and beware idle Excuſes, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.13</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="139" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>139.</label> Our beſt actions are <hi>Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit</hi> or <hi>Corrupt:</hi> ſee <hi>Job</hi> 14.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="140" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>140.</label> 'Tis <hi>fearfull</hi> to continue <hi>in</hi> ſin, and <hi>hard</hi> to get <hi>out</hi> of it: ſee <hi>Ap.</hi> 350. compare <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.1. with <hi>Jerem.</hi> 13.23.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="141" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105695:27"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>141.</label> Our thoughts of <hi>GOD</hi> are, what he will do <hi>with</hi> us, <hi>for</hi> us, <hi>by</hi> us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="142" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>142.</label> 'Tis better for us to be <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi> for our wickedneſs, than <hi>proudly</hi> to boaſt of our <hi>holineſs,</hi> Luke 18.10.11,12,13,14.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="143" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>143.</label> That Charity which <hi>begins</hi> at home, muſt not <hi>end</hi> at home. <hi>Mat</hi> 7.12. <hi>Chap.</hi> 22. <hi>verſe</hi> 39.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="144" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>144.</label> A <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> reproof may ſerve as a Rudder to <hi>alter</hi> a mans <hi>Courſe</hi> a better way: ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.23.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="145" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>145.</label> We are loaden with <hi>light</hi> Conceits and <hi>heavy</hi> Cares: <hi>with lead and feathers the back is broke.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="146" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:105695:28"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>146.</label> The wicked <hi>think</hi> the godly to be Fools: but the godly <hi>know</hi> the wicked to be Fools <hi>experimentally.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="147" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>147.</label> In our Indiſpoſitions, Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Afflictions let us look to the <hi>Reward,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.16,17,18. Heb. 12.1,2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="148" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>148.</label> The <hi>giving</hi> of the Law was <hi>terrible:</hi> oh what ſhall the <hi>Day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts be?</hi> Exod. 19.18. and 20,18,19. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 7,8,9.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="149" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>149.</label> Prophane men are <hi>vicious</hi> both in Mirth and Anger; <hi>ſtill fooliſh or frantick,</hi> Prov. 29 9.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="150" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>150.</label> 
                           <hi>Afflictions</hi> are as <hi>Sampſons</hi> Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they afford the <hi>honey</hi> of <hi>inſtruction</hi> ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.71. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12,10,11.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="151" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105695:28"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>151.</label> 
                           <hi>Cheerfulneſſe</hi> is like Oyle, it makes us <hi>prompt</hi> and <hi>ready</hi> to good duties, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="152" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>152.</label> 
                           <hi>Babes</hi> are nouriſhed at the Mouth, but <hi>new-born Babes</hi> at the Eare, <hi>Job</hi> 12.11. <hi>Chapter</hi> 34.3 with 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="153" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>153.</label> 
                           <hi>Afflicting</hi> ſorrow <hi>bewails</hi> ſin; but <hi>affecting</hi> ſorrow <hi>forſakes</hi> ſin; ſee <hi>Matthew</hi> 27.3,4. and <hi>Pſalme</hi> 51.2,10,11.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="154" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>154.</label> 
                           <hi>Diſtraction</hi> cures not <hi>Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Yielding</hi> never <hi>conquers; Believe not thy own unbelief.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="155" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>155.</label> 
                           <hi>Beauty</hi> is like an <hi>Almanacke;</hi> 'tis very <hi>ſoon out of date,</hi> Iſa. 40.6,7. with <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.30.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="156" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105695:29"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>156.</label> 
                           <hi>Order</hi> is <hi>pleaſant</hi> in Conceit, <hi>plaine</hi> in Demonſtration, <hi>ſure</hi> in Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="157" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>157.</label> Conſolations are for the <hi>well-being</hi> of the Soul: Faith and Repentance prove the <hi>being</hi> of grace.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="158" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>158</label> Deliberation and Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are the <hi>wiſe mans</hi> Oares, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. verſe. 28. to the 34. learn <hi>Fore-caſt</hi> and <hi>Reſolution.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="159" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>159.</label> Carnall Reaſon, and Self-love are the very <hi>vitals</hi> of the <hi>old man.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, are the Devills <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="160" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>160.</label> Boldneſs makes many go <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> their time, <hi>beyond</hi> their ſtrength, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. <hi>verſe</hi> 13. and 16. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.11.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="161" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105695:29"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>161.</label> Errour in <hi>practice</hi> is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with <hi>ſhame;</hi> Errour in <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> with <hi>pride.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="162" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>162.</label> Enemies may <hi>croſſe</hi> us, and <hi>hinder</hi> us on Earth, and yet <hi>further</hi> us to Heaven, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17,18.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="163" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>163.</label> 
                           <hi>Death</hi> is <hi>welcome</hi> when he ſindes us in <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> not in <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Security,</hi> Rev. 14.13. Matth. 24.45. to the end.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="164" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>164.</label> Faith and Works are as the Ship and wares; Both are <hi>loſt,</hi> or <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, James</hi> 2.14. to the end.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="165" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>165.</label> 
                           <hi>Diſcontent</hi> makes wants where none are, and <hi>encreaſes evills</hi> that <hi>be.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="166" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:105695:30"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>166.</label> 
                           <hi>A flictions</hi> are like a <hi>ſhowre</hi> of Raine: they make <hi>much noyſe,</hi> but <hi>hurt</hi> us not; they <hi>wet,</hi> but not <hi>wound.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="167" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>167.</label> 
                           <hi>Infants</hi> do <hi>ſuck</hi> but <hi>weakly</hi> though there be <hi>Milk enough;</hi> we are <hi>ſtreightned</hi> only in our <hi>ſelves;</hi> ſee 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.12.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="168" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>168.</label> 
                           <hi>Action</hi> is the Crown of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance</hi> is the Crown of <hi>Action;</hi> ſee <hi>Aphor.</hi> 185.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="169" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>169.</label> 
                           <hi>GOD</hi> works <hi>in</hi> us, <hi>for</hi> us, <hi>by</hi> us, bleſſed be his <hi>glorious</hi> Name, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="170" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>170.</label> The falls of <hi>Profeſsors</hi> bring <hi>grief</hi> to the <hi>godly,</hi> and <hi>ſcorne</hi> to the <hi>wicked,</hi> ſee 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.14.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="171" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:105695:30"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>171.</label> 
                           <hi>Grace</hi> is but <hi>little</hi> encreaſed in thoſe, who <hi>envie</hi> grace in others: <hi>(and indeed grace is too good for that vice.)</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="172" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>172.</label> 
                           <hi>Contemplation</hi> to the ſoul is like <hi>Mirth</hi> and <hi>Recreation</hi> to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.22. and 18.1.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="173" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>173.</label> 
                           <hi>Mortification</hi> is <hi>in</hi> us indeed, but not of us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1,25. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="174" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>174.</label> 
                           <hi>Grace</hi> works in us Contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for our <hi>own</hi> ſins, and compaſſion for <hi>others</hi> ſins, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.136.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="175" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>175.</label> 
                           <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> is the <hi>worſt</hi> ſin for <hi>GOD</hi> to judge, and the <hi>laſt</hi> ſin for <hi>Man</hi> to judge, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9 10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="176" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:105695:31"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>176.</label> 
                           <hi>Mans Life</hi> is like a <hi>Bottle</hi> of <hi>wine;</hi> Moderation makes it <hi>laſt long, Probatum eſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="177" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>177.</label> We muſt, like Mariners <hi>looke up,</hi> the better to order our Courſe <hi>below;</hi> ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 3,5,6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="178" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>178.</label> 
                           <hi>Love</hi> is a Grace, which <hi>doth moſt,</hi> and <hi>diſtruſts leaſts,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.4,5. &amp;c. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4,9,10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="179" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>179.</label> 
                           <hi>Love</hi> is a debt that muſt be <hi>ſo paid,</hi> that ſtill it is <hi>daily owing;</hi> ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.1.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="180" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>180.</label> 
                           <hi>Pride</hi> makes us, like <hi>ſwolne members,</hi> to <hi>do little</hi> and <hi>ſuffer leſſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="181" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:105695:31"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>181.</label> 
                           <hi>Reaſon</hi> is like the <hi>Sunne;</hi> it ſhewes <hi>all under it, nothing above it.</hi> So <hi>Solomon</hi> oft hints in his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="182" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>182.</label> 
                           <hi>Patience</hi> ſuffers <hi>evills preſent,</hi> and <hi>waites</hi> for <hi>good</hi> to <hi>come,</hi> Rom. 12.12. compared with <hi>Pſalme</hi> 37.7. and <hi>James</hi> 5.7,11.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="183" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>183.</label> There is <hi>nothing terrible</hi> in Death, but that our life hath <hi>made</hi> it ſo. O <hi>never</hi> forget that!</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="184" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>184.</label> 
                           <hi>Reproof</hi> is very <hi>grievous</hi> where <hi>Grace</hi> is <hi>wanting,</hi> ſee <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 141.5. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.8. and 13.1.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="185" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>185.</label> 
                           <hi>Perſeverance</hi> addes a Luſtre to our <hi>Graces,</hi> as <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arniſh</hi> does to the <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="186" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:105695:32"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>186.</label> 
                           <hi>Perſecutions, Proſperity,</hi> and <hi>Errours</hi> diſcover Hypocrites. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.21. <hi>Job</hi> 21.7. to 16. <hi>Palme</hi> 40.4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="187" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>187,</label> 
                           <hi>Old</hi> love being <hi>rooted</hi> ſtill <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivies</hi> upon <hi>freſh</hi> Occaſions; as in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>az,</hi> Ruth 2.11. and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="188" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>188.</label> 
                           <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> is bred of <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> and <hi>preſerves</hi> that which <hi>bred</hi> it, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 67.5 7. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 50. laſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="189" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>189</label> 
                           <hi>Thankefulneſſe</hi> is a Sacrifice <hi>moſt acceptable</hi> to <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>leaſt pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> to <hi>Man,</hi> Pſal. 50 8 to the 15.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="190" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>190.</label> Things <hi>wittie</hi> and <hi>pretty</hi> are not alwaies <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>pithie. The Tulip has rich Colours, but a beggerly Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="191" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:105695:32"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>191.</label> 
                           <hi>Ambition</hi> is the danger of the higher, <hi>Contention</hi> of the lower ſort of <hi>people.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="192" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>192.</label> 
                           <hi>Time</hi> is like a Serpent with his <hi>tayle</hi> in his <hi>mouth,</hi> we ſee not the <hi>end</hi> of it, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.22. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.24.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="193" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>193.</label> 
                           <hi>Time</hi> is alwaies <hi>paſſing:</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity is alway <hi>ſtanding ſtill. Time is a River: Eternity the Sea.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="194" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>194.</label> All our labour muſt be uſed with <hi>Prayer,</hi> but Prayer muſt not be <hi>all our labour,</hi> Epheſ. 6.13. to the 19.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="195" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>195.</label> 
                           <hi>Affliction</hi> is but our <hi>Shepherds dog;</hi> he comes not to <hi>devour</hi> us, but <hi>reduce</hi> us to the <hi>fold.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="196" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:105695:33"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>196.</label> The ſins of <hi>GODS</hi> people are a <hi>ſurprizall</hi> not a <hi>Contrivall</hi> (for the moſt part)</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="197" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>197.</label> No power, but that which at firſt did <hi>form</hi> us, is able to <hi>reform</hi> us alſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="198" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>198.</label> 
                           <hi>Naturall light</hi> is of it <hi>ſelf</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to <hi>damne</hi> us, but not enough to <hi>ſave</hi> us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12. to 16. with <hi>Chap</hi> 1.20.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="199" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>199.</label> They that would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in <hi>the day of the LORD,</hi> muſt make conſcience of the <hi>LORDS Day.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="200" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>200.</label> Thy portion in Heaven is <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> let me haſten to a <hi>perfect fitneſſe</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:105695:33"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Silver Sayings,</hi> or <hi>A Pocket-companion</hi>
                     </head>
                     <head>The ſecond part, by <hi>N.C.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div n="201" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>201.</label> The whole Creation is full of <hi>labour</hi> and <hi>noyſe:</hi> only in the Creators Boſome is <hi>reſt</hi> and <hi>quietneſſe;</hi> ſee <hi>Pſa.</hi> 73.25.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="202" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>202.</label> Greedineſſe of <hi>pleaſure</hi> makes men take <hi>much</hi> pains here, to ſuffer <hi>more</hi> hereafter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="203" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>203.</label> Take heed of an <hi>Agrippa,</hi> or a <hi>Not-quiete: Almoſt was never ſaved,</hi> Acts 26.28. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="204" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>204.</label> One honeſt <hi>Practitioner</hi> will out-ballance a throng of <hi>buſie-brain'd Skepticques</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="205" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>205.</label> He who looſes <hi>All for</hi> Chriſt, ſhall looſe nothing <hi>by</hi> Chriſt, but <hi>find</hi> all again <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> Mat. 19.29.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="206" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:105695:34"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>206.</label> If the <hi>Mercies</hi> of <hi>God</hi> lead us, to <hi>Repentance, Repentance</hi> will lead us to the <hi>God of Mercies,</hi> Rom. 2.4. Iſa. 55.7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="207" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>207.</label> We read that <hi>GOD</hi> had <hi>too many</hi> to fight his Battails, but never that he had <hi>too few,</hi> Judg. 7.2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="208" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>208.</label> The <hi>Curſe</hi> of <hi>Meroz</hi> doth not prove <hi>Gods defect,</hi> but only chides <hi>Mans neglect,</hi> Judg. 5.23. and 1 Sam. 14.6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="209" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>209.</label> We ſhould <hi>pray</hi> and <hi>endeavor</hi> that our <hi>ſorrow</hi> for <hi>ſin</hi> may drown all our <hi>ſinfull ſorrow,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="210" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>210.</label> 
                           <hi>Thy will be done,</hi> is the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> Prayer for <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> to <hi>utter,</hi> or <hi>God</hi> to <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,</hi> Matth. 26.39.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="211" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:105695:34"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>211.</label> Commonly where <hi>preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> leads the <hi>vann,</hi> there <hi>Deſperation</hi> brings up the <hi>rear.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="212" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>212.</label> The <hi>worſe</hi> the <hi>world</hi> is, the <hi>letter</hi> let <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> be; and the <hi>harder</hi> the Times, the <hi>ſofter</hi> let our Hearts be.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="213" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>213.</label> It argues <hi>little Wit,</hi> and <hi>leſſe Grace</hi> to prefer an <hi>uncertainty</hi> before a <hi>Certainty,</hi> Prov. 17.16.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="214" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>214.</label> Thoſe who add <hi>affliction</hi> to <hi>affliction,</hi> God will ſuperadd <hi>iniquity</hi> to their <hi>iniquity,</hi> Pſal. 79.26.27.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="215" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>315.</label> A <hi>little</hi> Dirt and Ayr, and a <hi>great deale</hi> of Sin, this is that <hi>proud</hi> thing called, MAN.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="216" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:105695:35"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>216.</label> If my <hi>ſins</hi> dye, while my <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> lives, when my <hi>Body</hi> dies my <hi>Soul</hi> ſhall live, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3,4,5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="217" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>217.</label> Thoſe who are troubled moſt <hi>for</hi> ſin, ſhall be troubled leaſt <hi>with</hi> ſin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.3,4,5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="218" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>218.</label> Thoſe that have <hi>mortall war</hi> with ſin, ſhall have <hi>immortall peace</hi> with God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.15,16,17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="219" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>219.</label> We may read a mans <hi>true</hi> Converſion in his <hi>faithfull</hi> Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. The Life is from the Heart.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="220" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>220.</label> An Hypocrite is not <hi>himſelf</hi> unleſſe he be miſtaken for <hi>another.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="221" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:105695:35"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>221.</label> Commonly there is but ſmall correſpondency betwixt a <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller</hi> and an <hi>Impropriator;</hi> The one would have all himſelf: the other, every man a ſhare. Both good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="222" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>222.</label> God never unſheaths the Sword of his <hi>Juſtice;</hi> till our <hi>flinty</hi> Hearts turn the <hi>edge</hi> of his <hi>Mercy.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="223" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>223.</label> Our Saviour is a <hi>Lyon</hi> for Power and Might; yet a <hi>Lamb</hi> for Patience and Meekneſſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.7. with <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.5,12. and <hi>Chapter</hi> 6.15,16,17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="224" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>224.</label> Build not upon <hi>futurity. Health</hi> is better than <hi>Phyſick, Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ſweeter than a <hi>Cure.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="225" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:105695:36"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>225.</label> 
                           <hi>Sinfull</hi> Craft is a ſhelter for <hi>Fooles;</hi> what is <hi>offenſive</hi> to God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>defenſive</hi> to Man.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="226" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>226.</label> In Prayer we ſhould <hi>not</hi> ſo much <hi>affect Expreſſion,</hi> as <hi>expreſſe Affection,</hi> Prov. 23.26. Pſalm 25.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Iſa. 29.13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="227" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>227.</label> God accepteth our <hi>pooreſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours,</hi> yet we under-value his <hi>rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Favours,</hi> 2 Cor. 8.12. Rom. 2.4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="228" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>228.</label> Lay not thy head to Reſt untill thou haſt got an <hi>Intereſt</hi> in <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting</hi> Reſt. See 403.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="229" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>229.</label> One ſinfull thought make Forfeiture of the Body to the <hi>worm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> and the Soul to the <hi>Devils,</hi> Gal. 3.10</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="230" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:105695:36"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>230.</label> A gracious heart is <hi>aſhamed</hi> of nothing but <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>proud</hi> of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his <hi>Saviour.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="231" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>231.</label> A prayerleſſe wretch is <hi>dead</hi> in ſin; for what Ayre is to the Body, Prayer is to the Soul.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="232" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>232.</label> The Devill <hi>ſupplants</hi> us in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> but God <hi>tranſplants</hi> us into the <hi>ſecond.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="233" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>33.</label> No Sin, or Mercy can be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>ſmall</hi> in it Self, and <hi>properly,</hi> but <hi>comparatively</hi> it may.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="234" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>234.</label> Some <hi>Giants</hi> are Dwarſes in reſpect of Others, and ſome <hi>Dwarfes</hi> are Giants compared with Others.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="235" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:105695:37"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>235.</label> Thoſe Eyes that have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the In-le s to <hi>ſweet Lust,</hi> ſhould be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Out-lets of <hi>ſalt Tears,</hi> Luke 7.37 38.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="236" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>236.</label> A <hi>good</hi> man in <hi>ill</hi> Compan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> is like a <hi>green ſtick</hi> among <hi>dry</hi> ones<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they may <hi>fire</hi> Him, not He <hi>quen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="237" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>237.</label> What ever we work <hi>for God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God</hi> works firſt <hi>in us:</hi> ſo there is <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> plea for Mans <hi>pride,</hi> but much fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Gods praiſe. Eſa.</hi> 26.12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="238" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>238.</label> A <hi>bad</hi> man <hi>would</hi> faine be <hi>worſe,</hi> but a <hi>good</hi> man <hi>chides</hi> himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> for being no <hi>better.</hi> Compare <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> with <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.19.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="239" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:105695:37"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>239.</label> 
                           <hi>Bathſheba's</hi> Bathing proves <hi>Davids</hi> Defilement; but <hi>Davids</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filement becomes his <hi>own Waſhing.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="240" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>240</label> A <hi>beggerly reward</hi> Iames Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, but a <hi>bounteous Recompence</hi> will ſet it on its <hi>Feet</hi> again.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="241" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>241.</label> 'Tis <hi>abundantly</hi> better to <hi>prevent</hi> the Maladie, then to <hi>invent</hi> the Remedie. <hi>Principiis obſta,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="242" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>242</label> Gods <hi>Care</hi> of us, and our <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations</hi> of Him are <hi>ſweeter</hi> then the Droppings of the Virgin Honey-Comb.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="243" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>243</label> Our <hi>own</hi> Miſcarriages <hi>teach</hi> us, better buy Wiſdom <hi>dear,</hi> then <hi>die</hi> a Fool. See <hi>Aph.</hi> 146.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="244" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:105695:38"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>244</label> A <hi>wicked</hi> Wretch may be in a <hi>good</hi> Mood, and a <hi>good</hi> Soul may be in an <hi>ill</hi> Temper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="245" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>245</label> As there is no <hi>good</hi> Motion, but is <hi>from</hi> God, ſo there is no true Reſt, but si in God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="246" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>246</label> It argues much <hi>light</hi> to <hi>ſee</hi> lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſins; but it argues much <hi>life</hi> to ſee the ſame, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.8.12.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="247" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>247</label> Oh that we did but <hi>ſpend</hi> as much Time, and <hi>take</hi> as much pains with our <hi>Hearts,</hi> as our <hi>Heads,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3,4,5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="248" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>248</label> The <hi>beſt</hi> men may read their own Principles in the worſt mens practices, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10,11.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="249" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:105695:38"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>249</label> Thoſe that will not <hi>pray</hi> till they are <hi>Saints,</hi> will not go into the <hi>Water</hi> till they can <hi>ſwim.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="250" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>250</label> To make to the <hi>Creature</hi> for ſhelter againſt <hi>Gods wrath,</hi> is to run into the <hi>River</hi> to eſcape <hi>Rain.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="251" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>251</label> 
                           <hi>Spiritual Endowments</hi> are the better for <hi>uſe,</hi> and never the <hi>worſe</hi> for <hi>wearing,</hi> Mat. 6.20. Luk. 12.23.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="252" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>252</label> We muſt not value things by the <hi>greatneſs</hi> of the Quantitie, but by the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of the Qualitie <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="253" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>253</label> 
                           <hi>Serious Matter</hi> ſtuft with <hi>light Flaſhes</hi> is like a <hi>grave Matron</hi> in a <hi>whoriſh dreſs.</hi> Note 1 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 5.22, and <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.3.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="254" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:105695:39"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>254</label> We are <hi>very</hi> inclinable to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe</hi> Others, that we may excuſe our Selves. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.12,13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="255" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>255</label> They that walk moſt <hi>conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly, lie down</hi> moſt <hi>comfortably, Pſal.</hi> 37.37. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="256" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>256</label> 'Tis but a <hi>ſtarveling</hi> Patience, that cannot out-live the <hi>other odde</hi> vexation, <hi>Jams</hi> 1.4.12. Chap. 5.7.10.11.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="257" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>257</label> To excuſe the default by Drunkenneſs is no <hi>Extenuation</hi> of the guilt, but <hi>Agravation.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="258" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>258</label> 'Tis an <hi>uncharitable</hi> Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to cenſure that for a <hi>love</hi> of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, which was but an <hi>errour</hi> of Love, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.28.29.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="259" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:105695:39"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>259</label> To <hi>tempt</hi> a man to Evill, and then after-wards to <hi>accuſe</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne</hi> him is Devilliſh.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="260" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>260</label> We ſhould rather forget to <hi>eat</hi> when we are an <hi>hungry,</hi> then to <hi>bleſs</hi> God when we are <hi>full.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="261" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>261</label> We muſt neither <hi>doat</hi> on our <hi>own</hi> ſelf-ſufficiencie nor <hi>doubt</hi> of Gods <hi>All-ſucfficiencie, Gen.</hi> 17.1 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. compare <hi>John</hi> 15.5. with <hi>Phil.</hi> 4 13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="262" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>262</label> Give the <hi>LORD of HOTS</hi> his <hi>due:</hi> Man <hi>fights,</hi> but GOD <hi>alone conquers,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.47. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="263" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>263</label> For the moſt part we diſcern Benefits and Favours better <hi>abſent</hi> then <hi>preſent, Hoſ.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 78.34. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.16.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="264" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:105695:40"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>264</label> 'Tis a <hi>good</hi> wind blowes <hi>no</hi> man <hi>hurt,</hi> but a <hi>better</hi> that blows <hi>all</hi> men <hi>good,</hi> ſuch is Mercy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.9.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="265" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>265</label> 'Tis more feaſable to <hi>be</hi> well, then to <hi>know</hi> it, and eaſier to <hi>have</hi> happineſs, then to <hi>find</hi> it, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.42. <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.16.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="266" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>266</label> 
                           <hi>Gods word</hi> is a <hi>Fire,</hi> which turns all where it faſtens into its <hi>own nature</hi> and <hi>qualitie,</hi> Jer. 5.14. and ch. 23.29. and ch. 20.9.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="267" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>267</label> Thoſe who doe what <hi>becomes</hi> them, never need fear what becomes of them, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="268" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>268</label> A ſouls union with Chriſt is eaſily demonſtrable by its <hi>thirſting deſire</hi> of Communion with him, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.11. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="269" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:105695:40"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>269</label> Nature is a <hi>Law,</hi> Cuſtome is a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> but Obſtinacy is a <hi>full grown Devil:</hi> ſee <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.23. and <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="270" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>270</label> A <hi>diſturbed Mind</hi> is like <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi> Waters, the worſt Looking glaſs that can be for <hi>ſelf reflexions, I ſay</hi> 57.20.21.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="271" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>271</label> 
                           <hi>A good Bruit</hi> is better then a <hi>wicked Man,</hi> and Children had better have been <hi>ſtill born,</hi> then live and die <hi>ſtubborn.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="272" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>272</label> They that are <hi>cruel</hi> to a man becauſe he is a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> ſtab <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Eye.</hi> Beware your <hi>thoughts,</hi> ſee, <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.8.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="273" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>273</label> 'Tis more tolerable to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the <hi>Worſt</hi> in the <hi>beſt</hi> things, then the <hi>Beſt</hi> in the <hi>worſt</hi> things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="274" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:105695:41"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>274</label> Look how much we <hi>arrogate</hi> unto our own applauſe, ſo much we <hi>derogate</hi> from <hi>Gods</hi> praiſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="275" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>275</label> 
                           <hi>Terreſtrial</hi> Joyes are <hi>trifling</hi> Toyes: Time takes them from <hi>Vs,</hi> or Death takes us from <hi>them.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="276" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>276.</label> The <hi>Slug-a-bed</hi> wakes, but his Heart <hi>ſleeps;</hi> the <hi>Good-husband</hi> ſleeps, but his Heart <hi>wakes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="277" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>277.</label> A <hi>good converſation</hi> is the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n</hi> of the <hi>good. Love,</hi> and <hi>Live,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.11. ch. 4.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="278" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>278</label> Where there is great <hi>ſolitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> there had need be no ſmall <hi>ſelf-warineſs,</hi> Gen. 2.18. Eccl. 4.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="279" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:105695:41"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>279.</label> 
                           <hi>Sinfull pleaſures</hi> wil not quit the <hi>coſt</hi> and <hi>paines</hi> we are at for the procurement of them, <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 1.2,8.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="280" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>280</label> 'Tis a <hi>beggerly</hi> blaze that hath not warmth enough to pay for its <hi>blowing,</hi> ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50. to the end.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="281" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>281.</label> Nip ſinne in the <hi>Budd.</hi> It is eaſier blowing out a <hi>Candle,</hi> then an <hi>Houſe</hi> on fire. See the 42. ſaying.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="282" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>282.</label> 
                           <hi>Spiritual</hi> Prudence is like <hi>Salt</hi> of <hi>litle Bulke,</hi> but of exceeding great <hi>Efficacie,</hi> ſee <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.29.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="283" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>283</label> By <hi>practiſing</hi> one Sermon, we <hi>prepare</hi> our ſelves the better to heare another, <hi>John</hi> 7.17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="284" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:105695:42"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>284</label> Some go to Sea to learn to <hi>pray;</hi> and inſtead thereof, I think, learn to <hi>ſwear.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="285" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>285</label> 'Tis an <hi>heavy</hi> thing to fall out of the throne of <hi>Ambition</hi> into the pit of <hi>Perdition, Iſay</hi> 14.12,13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="286" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>286</label> They that will go to Heaven, muſt look to be <hi>wet</hi> by the way; but though <hi>wet,</hi> they muſt not be weary. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="287" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>287</label> He that points at Earth with <hi>one finger,</hi> had need look up to heaven with <hi>both eyes,</hi> ſee <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1.2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="288" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>288</label> Uſe your Will: But <hi>bitter</hi> Phyſick is farre more deſirable, then <hi>ſweet</hi> poyſon. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="289" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:105695:42"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>289</label> This life is our <hi>ſeed time,</hi> the <hi>valley of Tears</hi> is our tranſitory to the <hi>Mountain of Glorification.</hi> Pſal. 84 6. Judg. 2.1,4,5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="290" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>290</label> 
                           <hi>Sweet</hi> Luſt is like the <hi>Bee</hi> with <hi>honey</hi> in the mouth, but a <hi>sting</hi> in the tayle; ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.32.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="291" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>291</label> If the End can be had without the Means, we may expect that our <hi>Bread</hi> ſhould grow ready <hi>baked.</hi> ſee <hi>James</hi> 5.7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="292" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>292</label> Chriſt ſets not the <hi>beſt</hi> ſide <hi>outward</hi> like <hi>man,</hi> but reſerves the <hi>beſt wine</hi> till the <hi>laſt,</hi> John 2.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="293" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>293</label> To <hi>neglect</hi> the means, or to make them our <hi>bottome</hi> for confidence are a like <hi>atheiſticall,</hi> ſee <hi>Aphor.</hi> 111.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="294" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:105695:43"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>294</label> The <hi>Corruption</hi> of the beſt is the <hi>worſt:</hi> the <hi>amendment</hi> of the <hi>worſt</hi> is the beſt of all, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 32.20 <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 6.4,5,6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12.13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="295" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>295</label> What a <hi>ſnailes-pace</hi> the Soul moves Heaven-ward, while ſhe groans under this bodily <hi>ſhell!</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="297" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>297</label> The ſame Truth ſpeaks <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation</hi> to the <hi>humble</hi> Soul, and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation</hi> to the <hi>proud</hi> Spirit, as <hi>Jerem.</hi> 17.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="297" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>297</label> Many times <hi>internal</hi> Depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Heart non-plus all <hi>externall</hi> Expreſſions of Hand or Tongue. <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="298" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>298</label> The Body ſometimes <hi>bleeds,</hi> though the Eyes <hi>weep not:</hi> and why may not the Soul do the like?</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="299" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:105695:43"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>299.</label> Now and then we may read the Heart in the Face, and the <hi>Sin</hi> in the <hi>judgement,</hi> Judg. 1.7. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.33</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="300" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>300</label> The <hi>ſmalleſt</hi> Bleſſing we have is undeſcrved <hi>à Priori,</hi> and Irrequita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>à Poſteriori.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="301" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>301</label> To be afraid of doing <hi>evill</hi> is a very <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>honourable</hi> kind of <hi>cowardlineſs, Gen.</hi> 29. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="302" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>302</label> Good <hi>Inclinations</hi> and <hi>Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> are <hi>both</hi> from <hi>GOD</hi> alone: he <hi>wills</hi> the work, and works the will, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="303" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>303.</label> 'Tis the Devils May-game, to ſet a mans <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> together by the Ears. See 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. and <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="304" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:105695:44"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>304</label> There is no place too <hi>holy</hi> for God, but there is a place too <hi>high</hi> for him, the <hi>proud</hi> heart, ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.1.2. and ch. 57.15. with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="305" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>305</label> 
                           <hi>Sweet</hi> Rarities are <hi>difficults: Roſes</hi> are armed with <hi>Prickles, Honey</hi> is engariſon'd with <hi>Bees.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="306" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>306</label> One Grain of <hi>reall</hi> Honeſty will outballance many <hi>Mountains</hi> of <hi>ſhifting</hi> Subtilty.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="307" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>307</label> Thoſe are the <hi>beſt</hi> Books that do not bribe us <hi>from,</hi> but ſend us <hi>to</hi> the Scriptures, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="308" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>308</label> As God loves a <hi>cheerfull gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> ſo he <hi>Himſelf</hi> loves to <hi>give cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> Ja. 1.5. with 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="309" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:105695:44"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>309</label> Many are <hi>rich</hi> without <hi>Money,</hi> and <hi>merry</hi> without <hi>Laughter,</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi> without <hi>Applauſe, James</hi> 2.5. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.29.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="310" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>310</label> As too <hi>much</hi> Learning makes a man <hi>mad,</hi> ſo too <hi>little</hi> makes him a <hi>Fool.</hi> Ponder that, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.24. with <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="311" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>311</label> A <hi>droppe</hi> of Gods Blood is enough to ſweeten an whole <hi>Ocean</hi> of ſin and ſorrow, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13,14.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="312" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>312</label> He makes a <hi>good</hi> market of a <hi>bad</hi> Commoditie, who vanquiſhes <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courteſies</hi> with <hi>kindneſs,</hi> Matth. 5. <hi>end.</hi> Luke 6.35,36,37.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="313" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>313</label> To recollect <hi>ſtale</hi> in juries, and bear in mind <hi>ſowre</hi> Grudges, is <hi>devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh childiſh,</hi> ſee <hi>Pro.</hi> 19.11. &amp; ch. 24.29.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="314" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:105695:45"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>314</label> The leaſt <hi>glimpſe</hi> of Gods <hi>Fvaour</hi> caſts a <hi>thick</hi> darkneſs upon all <hi>terriſtriall</hi> glory, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. <hi>Hab.</hi> end.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="315" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>315</label> How often can we do that in the <hi>face</hi> of God, which he would <hi>bluſh</hi> to <hi>ſpeak</hi> of to a <hi>fellow-ſinner, Pſal.</hi> 90.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.8.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="316" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>316</label> The <hi>bed-rid</hi> Patient is <hi>Gods</hi> Priſoner: the <hi>covetous</hi> Tarry at home the <hi>Devils</hi> in <hi>golden</hi> Fetters.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="317" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>317</label> An ill Conſcience beats the Hypocrite with <hi>ſand-bags,</hi> mortally, but yet <hi>imperceptibly.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="318" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>318</label> An Infant is in affect <hi>raſa ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula,</hi> a blanck-book, you may as yet write in it, <hi>what you pleaſe, Gen.</hi> 18.19. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6 7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="319" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:105695:45"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>319</label> 'Tis more tolerable to be a <hi>laviſh</hi> Prodigall, then to be a <hi>ſlaviſh</hi> Pinch-paunch <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. the 3 laſt and ch. 6. the 2 firſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="320" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>320</label> We cannot <hi>alwayes</hi> tell what's a clock in a mans <hi>Breaſt,</hi> by the Dyall of his <hi>Face. Fronti nulla Fides, Jer.</hi> 17.9.10 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16 7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="321" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>321</label> 'Tis miraculous for the Dead to Live again, but much more for the <hi>Life</hi> of the world to die.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="322" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>322.</label> What our prudence cannot cunningly <hi>for-goe,</hi> our patience muſt quietly <hi>undergoe.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="323" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>323.</label> Shew me the man that is <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vrurable</hi> to Others, and <hi>ſevere</hi> to Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and if I do not <hi>love</hi> Him, <hi>hate</hi> Me.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="324" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:105695:46"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>324</label> Both are a like <hi>abſurd,</hi> words out of <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> and works out of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Eccl. 3.1.7.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="325" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>325</label> Thoſe that open the Eyes of the <hi>blind,</hi> muſt <hi>hide</hi> Themſelves, that the <hi>Sun</hi> of Righteouſneſs may be <hi>ſeen</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="326" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>326</label> He who takes Reproof moſt willingly, leaſt <hi>deſerves</hi> it of any man; ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 98. &amp; 28.23.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="327" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>327</label> Where Folly is the <hi>ſeed,</hi> ſhame is the <hi>fruit;</hi> and where Luſt is the <hi>work,</hi> ſorrow is the <hi>wages,</hi> Rom. 6.21,23.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="328" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>328</label> When <hi>Peter</hi> looks upon the <hi>Sunne</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> it makes his Eyes <hi>water</hi> abundantly, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.61.62.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="329" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:105695:46"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>329</label> Our <hi>leaſt</hi> ſinnes out-vie our <hi>greateſt</hi> ſufferings: Gods <hi>leaſt</hi> Mercies excell our <hi>greateſt</hi> Praiſes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="330" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>330</label> Gods <hi>Word</hi> makes Children like the <hi>Aged,</hi> and keeps the Aged from being like <hi>Children,</hi> ſee <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.99.100.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="331" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>331</label> 
                           <hi>Humane</hi> Learning, Moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, hath its <hi>blemiſhes,</hi> its <hi>changes;</hi> and ſhines but with a <hi>borrowed</hi> lights 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="332" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>332</label> Till Converſion our hearts are but meer <hi>blotting paper,</hi> and our Thoughts but <hi>wild ſcriblings.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="333" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>333</label> He that <hi>feeds</hi> the Wolf, <hi>kills</hi> the Sheep, ſay the <hi>Jews:</hi> and he that <hi>ſpares</hi> a Luſt <hi>ſtabs</hi> a Soul, may <hi>we</hi> ſay.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="334" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:105695:47"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>334</label> God is the <hi>Heart-maker, Heart-ſearcher, Heart-mender, Heart-keeper,</hi> and <hi>Heart-ſatisfier,</hi> Pſal. 51.10. Jer. 17.10. Pſ. 4.6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="335" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>335</label> Many are ſo <hi>extream</hi> pieviſh againſt <hi>humane learning,</hi> that they have <hi>unlearnt</hi> all <hi>humanitie.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="336" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>336</label> The unbeliever dies of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint,</hi> as a preſt man: the Believers dies of <hi>choice</hi> like a true Voluntier.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="337" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>337</label> The world is <hi>full</hi> of Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: but thoſe Promiſes are <hi>empty per formances.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="338" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>338</label> We muſt not adventure to put off <hi>Repentance</hi> till we put on <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie:</hi> ſee 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="339" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:105695:47"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>339</label> Our Memories are meere Sives, they will neither retain the <hi>Flower,</hi> nor yet part with the <hi>Bran.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="340" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>340</label> The blind man eats many a <hi>Fly:</hi> Go to then, <hi>Blunderers beware Belzebub,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="341" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>341</label> They that will not ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively <hi>bow to CHRIST,</hi> ſhall irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verably be <hi>broken by</hi> Him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="342" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>342</label> They that will not ſee the <hi>KING</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> golden Scepter, ſhall ſurely <hi>feel</hi> his Iron Rod, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 2. <hi>all.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="343" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>343</label> The Art of <hi>prevention</hi> is every way better and ſafer, then the Art of <hi>invention.</hi> See <hi>Aph.</hi> 241.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="344" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:105695:48"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>344</label> 'Tis not the going <hi>into</hi> the Fornance, but the coming <hi>out,</hi> which demonſtrates the Mettall.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="345" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>345</label> Where the Remedie is worſe then the Diſeaſe, queſtionleſs there the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> is a FOOL.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="346" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>346</label> Where the Remedie is <hi>worſe</hi> then the Diſeaſe, it is <hi>better</hi> being <hi>ſick,</hi> then <hi>well,</hi> 2 King. 1.6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="347" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>347</label> Choak Luſt in the Embryo: Better <hi>ſtamp</hi> upon an <hi>Egge,</hi> then <hi>look</hi> upon a <hi>reigning</hi> Baſilisk.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="348" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>348</label> 'Tis but a <hi>mercileſs</hi> compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to <hi>preſerve</hi> that, which will ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly <hi>deſtroy</hi> our <hi>ſelves.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="349" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:105695:48"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>349</label> Remember Time <hi>paſt,</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Time <hi>preſent,</hi> and fore-ſtall Time <hi>future,</hi> Rev. 2.5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="350" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>350</label> If we make Mercy fewel for Luſt: certainly Luſt will make <hi>Vs</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ewel for <hi>Hell,</hi> Rom. 2.4,5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="351" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>351</label> There are many that have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>reat parts, and yet are very Fooles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or want of <hi>good</hi> Hearts.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="352" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>352</label> He who robs God of his <hi>firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>uits,</hi> forfeits the <hi>whole Crop</hi> to the <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>evil,</hi> Mal. 1.14. and ch. 3.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="353" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>353</label> Doe nothing without Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ght or Fore-caſt. A <hi>little</hi> warineſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>events <hi>much</hi> wearineſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="354" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:105695:49"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>354</label> Backward, nor forward are ſome good. A <hi>Churle</hi> is a <hi>Lurch,</hi> and a <hi>Nabal</hi> is a <hi>Laban.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="355" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>355</label> They who doe good <hi>again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> their Will, doubtleſs would as fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> do Evill <hi>with</hi> their Will.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="356" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>356</label> A <hi>good Hand-maid</hi> makes a <hi>good Houſe-wife,</hi> and a <hi>good Manſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> makes a <hi>good Master.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="357" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>357</label> He had need be <hi>extraordinary Patient,</hi> who has the <hi>Devil</hi> for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Doctor: ſee 2 <hi>Reg,</hi> 1.1,2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="358" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>358</label> Many Heathens by <hi>education</hi> prove Chriſtians by <hi>converſation:</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> many Chriſtians by <hi>education</hi> prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Heathens by <hi>converſation.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="359" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:105695:49"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>359</label> Men would be <hi>mute</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>ability,</hi> if they did but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their <hi>mutabilitie.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="360" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>360</label> 
                           <hi>Life</hi> is a <hi>puffe,</hi> God is our <hi>Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter:</hi> Let us do good according to our <hi>own</hi> Abilitie, and our <hi>Neighbours Neceſſitie,</hi> Gal. 6.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="361" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>361</label> 
                           <hi>One</hi> Default makes a thing <hi>imperfect,</hi> but <hi>all</hi> good Circumſtances go to make it <hi>perfect.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="362" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>362</label> To forbear doing <hi>ill,</hi> for want of <hi>Skill,</hi> and not of <hi>Will,</hi> is the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie of a <hi>Fool.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="363" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>363</label> Many a ſufficient Workman is <hi>well given,</hi> and yet his Labour and Pains is <hi>ill taken.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="364" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:105695:50"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>364</label> To do <hi>no ill</hi> makes not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>good</hi> Man; but to do <hi>no good</hi> makes an abſolute <hi>evill Man.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="365" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>365.</label> If we ſhew Mercy when wee can <hi>beſt ſpare</hi> it, God will return it when we <hi>most need</hi> it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.9,10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="366" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>366.</label> 
                           <hi>Believe not</hi> thy own Unbelief. 'Tis an <hi>ill</hi> Diſeaſe, where the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian is a <hi>Murtherer.</hi> Read 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.2. to the 7. Verſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="367" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>367.</label> He that hath never ſo much <hi>earneſt buſineſſe,</hi> muſt be at <hi>leiſure</hi> to Dye <hi>prepared,</hi> or <hi>unprepared.</hi> Luke 12.18,19,20.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="368" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>368.</label> The <hi>loſs</hi> of Evill is great <hi>gain.</hi> The Mortification of the <hi>Old</hi> men, is the Fortification of the <hi>New.</hi> Rom. 8.13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="369" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:105695:50"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>369.</label> 
                           <hi>Pray</hi> and <hi>Proſper; Aske</hi> and <hi>receive; Beg</hi> and <hi>ſpeed;</hi> but <hi>Nothing crave, Nothing have,</hi> Matth. 7.7. Jam. 4.2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="370" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>370.</label> The Supremacy of <hi>Reaſon</hi> muſt not be <hi>counter-byaſſed</hi> by the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularity of the <hi>Senſes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="371" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>371.</label> If poore ſinners would but be <hi>more dutifull,</hi> aſſuredly they would be <hi>leſſe doubtfull,</hi> 2 Cor. 9.7. Chap. 8.12.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="372" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>372.</label> Where the water is parcel'd out into ſo many Rivolets, the <hi>Main current</hi> ſtarves. See <hi>Luke</hi> 10.41,42. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="373" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>373.</label> They that <hi>rage</hi> againſt the wayes of <hi>GODS</hi> Providence, do but throw <hi>ſcalding Water</hi> to <hi>Windeward,</hi> See <hi>Job</hi> 9.4. Cha. 33.13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.22.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="374" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="76" facs="tcp:105695:51"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>374</label> 
                           <hi>Self-love</hi> is the quench coal of <hi>Brotherly-love,</hi> and <hi>Self-wil</hi> is the break neck of <hi>Self-denial,</hi> Phil. 2.4,21 Mat. 24.12. 2 Tim. 3.2,3,4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="375" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>375</label> 
                           <hi>Tart</hi> Reprehenſion from a <hi>kind</hi> Friend, is like Limmon and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, <hi>ſharp</hi> and <hi>ſweet,</hi> ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.5,6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141.5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="376" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>376</label> Patiently <hi>hear</hi> Admonition. Many that have lived <hi>Fearleſs,</hi> have died <hi>Earleſs.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="377" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>377</label> The Conqueſt of <hi>one</hi> Boſome Foe is worth <hi>many</hi> Tears, and <hi>much</hi> Time and Labour.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="378" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>378.</label> Diſpatch, Diſpatch, make what haſte we can poſſible, <hi>Night</hi> will bring us <hi>home.</hi> 1 Cor. 7.29, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="379" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:105695:51"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>379</label> 'Tis a mercifull Tyranny to <hi>wrack ſinne,</hi> and ſhew no favour to a <hi>Deſtroyer.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="380" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>380</label> Two hungry meales make the third a <hi>Glutton,</hi> two gluttonous meales make the third a <hi>ſtarveling.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="381" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>381</label> When we fight againſt God with his <hi>Own Mercies,</hi> we beat our ſelves with our <hi>Own Sinnes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="382" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>382</label> Our land is like <hi>Gydeons Fleece,</hi> Judg. 6.38. and yet our hearts (quite contrary) are like <hi>Gideons Fleece,</hi> verſe 40.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="383" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>383</label> The poor man is thus farre <hi>happy</hi> beyond others, in that he hath <hi>nothing</hi> to <hi>looſe:</hi> Se <hi>Job</hi> 1.21. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 9.7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="384" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:105695:52"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>314.</label> From Creatures we muſt neither <hi>beg</hi> nor <hi>buy</hi> Commendation, nor yet <hi>feare</hi> Condemnation.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="385" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>385.</label> 
                           <hi>Good drinke makes good blood.</hi> I but how? Juſt as <hi>good Water,</hi> makes <hi>good Pottage.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="386" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>386.</label> The Devill commonly cozens <hi>us,</hi> by perſwading us we cozen <hi>him.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="387" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>387.</label> A <hi>good mans</hi> Tongue many time ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>edly ſets an <hi>ill Dogs</hi> Teeth of work, <hi>ex inopinato.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="388" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>388.</label> He who is both <hi>prudent</hi> and <hi>innocent,</hi> ſhall neither <hi>deceive,</hi> nor be <hi>deceived,</hi> See <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.16.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="389" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:105695:52"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>389</label> The <hi>Higheſt, greateſt,</hi> and <hi>richeſt,</hi> are but Gods Beggers; we <hi>all</hi> do <hi>live</hi> by his <hi>love.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="390" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>390.</label> Wee muſt learn to promiſe with <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> &amp; to perform with <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Affection.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="391" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>391.</label> 
                           <hi>Weeping Eyes</hi> are not to be <hi>wincked</hi> at, nor yet to be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>dry Eyes;</hi> See <hi>Luke</hi> 7.38. <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.62.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="392" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>392.</label> The World is the Booke of the <hi>Creature:</hi> The Word is the Booke of the <hi>Creator</hi> too; ſee Pſalme 19.1.7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="393" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>393.</label> 'Tis humane to <hi>ſuffer ill,</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine to do <hi>good.</hi> Patience and Love will go through <hi>both.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:105695:53"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:105695:53"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <div n="394" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="80" facs="tcp:105695:54"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>394</label> A Schollar of <hi>great</hi> Reading and <hi>ſmall</hi> Parts, lives upon <hi>Collections</hi> and <hi>Exhibitions</hi> from Friends.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="395" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>395</label> He who makes <hi>great</hi> Promiſes and <hi>ſmall</hi> Performances, muſt expect <hi>great ſhame</hi> and <hi>ſmall Thanks<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="396" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>396</label> Many abuſe <hi>good will,</hi> and turn a <hi>ſacred Priviledge</hi> into a <hi>privie Sacriledge.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="397" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>397</label> Better do <hi>well</hi> and <hi>fare</hi> ill, then do <hi>ill,</hi> and fare <hi>worſe.</hi> Did not I tell you ſo before?</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="398" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>398</label> This World is for <hi>labour</hi> and <hi>appetite;</hi> the Next is for <hi>rest</hi> and <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction:</hi> Be patient then a while.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="399" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>399</label> Teach without Envy, Learn without Shame; then thou art both <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>humble.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="400" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="81" facs="tcp:105695:54"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>400</label> Where Love hath <hi>ingreſs,</hi> Thanks hath <hi>egreſs:</hi> and where Grace hath <hi>progreſs,</hi> Sin hath <hi>regreſs.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="401" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>401</label> 
                           <hi>Affection</hi> without <hi>Knowledge,</hi> is Heat without Light, like a <hi>cloſe hot</hi> Oven.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="402" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>402</label> 
                           <hi>Knowledge</hi> without <hi>Affection,</hi> is <hi>Light</hi> without <hi>Heat,</hi> like a <hi>froſty Moon ſhine.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="403" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>403</label> Let it be thy <hi>firm Reſolution</hi> to get thy <hi>full Abſolution,</hi> before thy <hi>finall Diſſolution,</hi> Mat. 5.25. ſee 228.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="404" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>404</label> 
                           <hi>Vp and be doing, and proſper.</hi> More die of the Lazies, then of Labour and Travail: See 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 22.16.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="405" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>405</label> A Brow of <hi>Braſs,</hi> and a Neck of <hi>Iron,</hi> procures an Heaven of <hi>Braſs,</hi> and an Earth of <hi>Iron,</hi> Jer. 3.3.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="406" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:105695:55"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>406.</label> Others <hi>Falls</hi> are not our <hi>Foot-ſtools,</hi> or ſtumbling-blocks, but rather our <hi>Looking glaſſes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="407" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>407.</label> Say not, <hi>God hath thrown ſuch an one by as an uſeleſs pot-ſheard:</hi> for, <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.19.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="408" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>408.</label> 
                           <hi>Deſpiſe</hi> none for their Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>deſpair</hi> of none for their Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe: <hi>Our times are in Gods hand,</hi> Pſal. 31.15.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="409" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>409.</label> God will not <hi>endure</hi> to ſee Pride <hi>ſtamp</hi> on Peace, Violence <hi>kick</hi> Mercy, nor Rigour <hi>over-maſter</hi> Love.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="410" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>410.</label> To bid <hi>carnall Security</hi> ſtill Conſcience, is but to ſet a Sleeper to <hi>Rock</hi> the Cradle.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="411" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:105695:55"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>411.</label> Under-value not the Poore: we cannot want the Duſt-man, the Dung-hill raker, the Chimney-ſweeper, nor the Gold-finder.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="412" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>412.</label> He that acts <hi>meerly</hi> from a principle of Power, Policy, and Self-will, ſhall ſurely fall by his <hi>own</hi> Contrivances, <hi>Job</hi> 5.12,13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="413" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>413.</label> It does me more good then my <hi>Victuals,</hi> to ſee but the Devil <hi>miſs</hi> of his <hi>Ayme</hi> and <hi>befoole himſelf,</hi> Job 5.12,13,14,15.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="414" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>414</label> Wee ſhould not thinke ſo much upon what <hi>others do,</hi> as upon what <hi>our ſelves ought</hi> to do, <hi>John</hi> 21.21,22.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="415" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>415.</label> 
                           <hi>Braſſe</hi> and <hi>Steele</hi> have ſlaine their <hi>thouſands</hi> of Bodies; but <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> their <hi>tenne thouſands</hi> of Souls.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="416" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:105695:56"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>416</label> 
                           <hi>Bad</hi> men (indeed I confeſs) have ſome <hi>good thoughts:</hi> I, but <hi>good men</hi> have <hi>more bad thoughts.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="417" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>417</label> Many <hi>hold forth</hi> ſo long, that at laſt, I fear they will hardly <hi>hold out</hi> to the laſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="418" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>418</label> They ſay, <hi>Deeds are male,</hi> and <hi>Words female:</hi> but I am ſure, <hi>Thoughts</hi> are <hi>doubtfull.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="419" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>419</label> That, whereon we <hi>lay out much</hi> (unleſs we are <hi>compleat</hi> fools) we lay <hi>up ſafe,</hi> Mat. 13.44.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="420" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>420</label> Ply well the Twig while it is <hi>green.</hi> If Youth be <hi>ſick</hi> of the <hi>Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots,</hi> Old-age will <hi>die</hi> of the <hi>Cannots.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="421" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:105695:56"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>421</label> 
                           <hi>Fierie Furie,</hi> and <hi>key-cold Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> opens the doors to a <hi>Luke-warm Chriſtianitie.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="422" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>422</label> I have told you often enough of it, That <hi>The poore in purſe are for Communitie: The poore in ſpirit are for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="423" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>423</label> One <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> in Heaven is worth more then all the <hi>Gems, Pearls, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> and <hi>Diadems</hi> on Earth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="424" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>424</label> 
                           <hi>Fellow-members</hi> mutually ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathize; but the <hi>whole Body</hi> condoles the <hi>ſick Heart.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="425" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>425</label> 
                           <hi>Brotherly-love</hi> is no <hi>looſer.</hi> The Head is <hi>beholding</hi> to the Feet, and the Belly is the Hands <hi>beſt Pay-master:</hi> ſee the 72. <hi>Aph.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="426" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:105695:57"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>426.</label> Mans <hi>Performances</hi> muſt learn to borrow ſtrength of Gods <hi>Promiſes,</hi> John 16.23. James 1.5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="427" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>427.</label> 'Tis more tolerable and ſafe to <hi>ſuffer</hi> the <hi>greateſt</hi> Injury, then to <hi>do</hi> the <hi>leaſt,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.6,7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="428" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>428.</label> Let us be thankfull for what we <hi>have,</hi> and we ſhall the better ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of God what we <hi>have</hi> not.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="429" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>429.</label> The Lord will bleſſe that <hi>Basket,</hi> and that <hi>Store,</hi> out of the which we do relieve the <hi>Poore,</hi> Luke 6.38. Eccleſ. 11.1,2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="430" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>430.</label> Wealthy I <hi>would</hi> be; for Live I <hi>may:</hi> but Honeſt I <hi>will be,</hi> for Dye I <hi>muſt,</hi> Jer. 17.9,10,11.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="431" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="87" facs="tcp:105695:57"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>431.</label> When we <hi>want</hi> Comforts, then we are <hi>mad</hi> for Anger: but when we <hi>have</hi> them, then we are <hi>mad</hi> for Joy.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="432" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>432.</label> Neither Creator, nor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would <hi>hurt</hi> us, if we would but be <hi>true</hi> to our <hi>own Soules,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="433" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>433.</label> We can never part with <hi>too much</hi> for Him, who parted with <hi>All</hi> that ever he had for <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> Phil. 2.7. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. He emptied or Evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Himſelf.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="434" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>434</label> Say not in thy heart, <hi>God is mercifull,</hi> therefore <hi>I may be ſinfull;</hi> but <hi>God is mercifull,</hi> therefore <hi>I muſt be thankefull.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="435" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>435.</label> A little that is good, is as <hi>much</hi> as I <hi>deſire,</hi> and more then I <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve:</hi> or elſe I am a very <hi>lyar,</hi> to ſay ſo. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.16. <hi>Gen</hi> 32.10.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="436" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="88" facs="tcp:105695:58"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>436</label> God will not beat his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <hi>for nothing,</hi> much leſs wil he beat them <hi>to nothing,</hi> Pſalm 107.17. and Jer. 10.24.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="437" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>437</label> We are <hi>greedie</hi> of Benefits when we want them, and yet we are <hi>ungratefull,</hi> when we have obtained them, ſee 456.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="438" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>438</label> As thoſe that <hi>will not</hi> work, <hi>muſt not</hi> eat, ſo thoſe that may not eat, <hi>cannot</hi> work, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.25. and a <hi>Theſ,</hi> 3.10. ſee <hi>Aph.</hi> 72.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="439" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>339</label> The <hi>young</hi> Storke nouriſhes the <hi>old</hi> one, and <hi>Children</hi> ſhould not altogether <hi>die</hi> in the <hi>Parents debt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="440" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>440</label> Many times as the Cat ſerves the Mouſe, even ſo the <hi>greater</hi> Thiefe leads the <hi>leſs</hi> to <hi>execution.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="441" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="89" facs="tcp:105695:58"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>441</label> The <hi>melancholly</hi> Soul fights with <hi>ſhadowes,</hi> and beats himſelf with his <hi>own</hi> weapons.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="442" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>442</label> That which <hi>breaks out</hi> in the Body or Skin, <hi>commonly went in</hi> firſt at the Head, <hi>Docet experientia rerum.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="443" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>443</label> True Riches by <hi>diſtribution</hi> feel no <hi>diminution,</hi> but by <hi>Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion get</hi> an <hi>Augmentation.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="444" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>444</label> 'Tis an ill Diſeaſe that <hi>hides</hi> it ſelf, and a <hi>ſoar beaten</hi> Child, that <hi>dares not</hi> Cry. Get that without book.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="445" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>445</label> To <hi>faſt</hi> and <hi>watch</hi> and <hi>pray,</hi> and then <hi>relapſe</hi> again, is to <hi>waſh</hi> our Hands, and <hi>ſnuff</hi> the Candle.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="446" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="90" facs="tcp:105695:59"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>446.</label> 
                           <hi>One</hi> Calling is enough at <hi>once,</hi> The <hi>deepeſt</hi> Engineers are not alwaies the <hi>richeſt</hi> Men.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="447" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>447.</label> One would think the Head ſhould lay to heart, what the Hand layes out of the Store-houſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.28.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="448" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>448.</label> There is no Patience in Hell; but we may be ſure, that there is an Hell in Impatience, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.26,27.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="449" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>449.</label> The <hi>whole</hi> world is <hi>full</hi> of Gods <hi>glory;</hi> And yet our <hi>Wicked</hi> Hearts are <hi>empty</hi> of his <hi>grace.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="450" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>450</label> Commit thy way to GOD, and ſubmit thy Will, and he will <hi>compoſe</hi> thy Affections, and <hi>diſpoſe</hi> thy Actions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.3. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.3.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="451" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="91" facs="tcp:105695:59"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>451.</label> What an Heaven would it be to our Souls, if we were but halfe ſo <hi>unwilling</hi> to <hi>ſin,</hi> as God is to <hi>puniſh?</hi> Lam. 3.33.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="452" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>452.</label> So groſſe is our folly, that We take <hi>more paines</hi> to be <hi>miſerable,</hi> then we <hi>need</hi> to do to be <hi>happy,</hi> Iſa. 55.1,2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="453" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>453.</label> Except Sin be <hi>ſeperate</hi> from our Souls, it will ſeperate our Souls from our Bodies, and <hi>both</hi> from God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.2. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="454" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>454.</label> What <hi>loades</hi> of Offences and Provocations does the Lord beare, long before ever he <hi>complains!</hi> Iſa. 43.24. <hi>Amos</hi> 2.13.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="455" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>455.</label> We are naturally more taken, with a <hi>grain</hi> of <hi>ſeeming</hi> Pleaſure, then a <hi>mountain</hi> of <hi>reall</hi> Profit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="456" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="92" facs="tcp:105695:60"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>456</label> We do contemptuouſly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der value Mercies in the <hi>enjoyment:</hi> but highly prize them at the <hi>removal,</hi> ſee the 437.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="457" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>457</label> Inſtead of conquering <hi>evil</hi> with <hi>goodneſs,</hi> we repay <hi>evil</hi> for <hi>good</hi> unto <hi>God himſelf,</hi> Iſa. 1.2. Deut. 32.5,6.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="458" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>458</label> God will aſſuredly anſwer our Prayers <hi>graciouſly,</hi> if our lives and converſations anſwer them ſo.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="459" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>459</label> Chriſts Excellency is exalted farther <hi>above</hi> the Heavens, then it is hence to the Heavens.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="460" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>460</label> The <hi>worſt</hi> thinks himſelf <hi>better</hi> then he <hi>is,</hi> and the <hi>beſt</hi> is <hi>worſe</hi> then he thinks himſelf.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="461" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="93" facs="tcp:105695:60"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>461</label> The beſt work that ever we can <hi>perform</hi> in thought, word and work, is to <hi>reform</hi> All, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.11.16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="462" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>462</label> Our moſt <hi>enlarged</hi> Prayers and Profeſſions can no more <hi>ſatisfie GOD themſelves,</hi> then <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Words</hi> can pay Debts.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="463" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>463</label> In <hi>God,</hi> not only We, but alſo our Graces, Comforts, and <hi>Vertues,</hi> do <hi>live, move,</hi> and <hi>exiſt,</hi> Ioh. 15.5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="464" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>464</label> We ſhould ſhun ſuch <hi>profits</hi> as purchaſe Gods <hi>diſpleaſure,</hi> and hate ſuch <hi>pleaſures</hi> as procure our Soules <hi>diſprofit.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="465" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>465</label> 
                           <hi>GOD</hi> needs nothing that <hi>we</hi> have, to <hi>felicitate</hi> Him, no more then the Sun needs a <hi>Candle</hi> to ſee Day by.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="466" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="94" facs="tcp:105695:61"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>466.</label> Never be weary of the <hi>godly</hi> Mans company: In good <hi>ſociety</hi> there ſhould be no <hi>ſatiety,</hi> Pſal. 16.3.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="467" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>467.</label> The Lord Jeſus hath more Compaſſion in ſtore, then <hi>all</hi> the <hi>World</hi> can make <hi>uſe</hi> of, or ſtand in <hi>need</hi> of.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="468" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>468.</label> The Soul is a Tree, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties are Branches, the Thoughts are Buds, the words are Leaves, the Actions are Fruit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="469" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>469.</label> That ſame Travailer that takes <hi>moſt heed</hi> to his Wayes, makes <hi>beſt ſpeede</hi> to his End, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.23,26.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="470" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>470.</label> We cannot <hi>think too bad</hi> of our ſelves, nor <hi>ſpeake good enough</hi> of God: Yet he <hi>prizes us,</hi> we <hi>ſlight Him.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="471" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:105695:61"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>471.</label> The Lord is not only a <hi>God hearing Prayers;</hi> but alſo (Iſa. 65.24.) preventing prayers.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="472" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>472.</label> The Godly mans <hi>down-fall,</hi> is his <hi>upriſing,</hi> the Wicked mans <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing</hi> is his <hi>down-fall,</hi> Pſal. 37.23,24. Pſal. 73.18,19.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="473" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>473.</label> 
                           <hi>Moſt</hi> men walk in the <hi>broad</hi> Way, and yet <hi>every</hi> man thinks to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at the <hi>ſtreight</hi> Gate, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.25.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="474" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>474.</label> There is no man living ſo <hi>Young,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>preſume,</hi> nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſo <hi>Old,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>deſpair</hi> of Mercy.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="475" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>475.</label> 
                           <hi>I</hi> muſt <hi>pray for the Churches perſecutors,</hi> and ſo I do: <hi>Lord, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give their ſinnes, and give,</hi> them <hi>leſſe Power,</hi> and <hi>us more Patience.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="476" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="96" facs="tcp:105695:62"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>476</label> He that cheats Himſelf is a <hi>fooliſh</hi> Knave: he that cheats the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is an <hi>honeſt</hi> Knave.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="477" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>477</label> Where is <hi>reall ſinceritie</hi> in the Life, there will be <hi>unwearied perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> till Death, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>laſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="478" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>478</label> That Eye will never endure to look the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>face,</hi> to which a <hi>Torch</hi> is <hi>tedious,</hi> ſee <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.5. and <hi>Aph.</hi> next.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="479" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>479</label> How ſhall any behold a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire,</hi> who cannot endure the <hi>ſight</hi> of a Saint? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. <hi>laſt</hi> ſee <hi>John</hi> 5.35.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="480" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>480</label> 'Tis a <hi>royal ſhame,</hi> when that vice is in a <hi>King</hi> that is <hi>intolerable</hi> in a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> Deut. 18.10,11. 1 Sam. 28.7.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="481" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="97" facs="tcp:105695:62"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>481.</label> Magiſtrates and Miniſters too oft (like the <hi>Sea</hi>) can tame <hi>others,</hi> but not <hi>themſelves,</hi> Rom. 2.17. to 25. with verſe, 1,2,3.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="482" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>482.</label> 'Tis an <hi>unconceivable</hi> Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to <hi>let ſlip</hi> the Occaſion of <hi>doing evill,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.14. 1 Theſ. 5.22.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="483" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>483.</label> Be our Voyage <hi>long,</hi> or <hi>ſhort, ſwift,</hi> or <hi>ſlow, proſperous</hi> or adverſe, We all <hi>anchor</hi> in the <hi>Earth.</hi> See <hi>Job.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> 26.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="484" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>484.</label> Take but out the Water, and ye ſhall find the Sea a <hi>Grave</hi> to bury <hi>thouſands</hi> among Fiſh-Wormes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="485" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>485.</label> The Devill <hi>promiſes</hi> like a <hi>Merchant,</hi> but he <hi>performes</hi> like a <hi>Man of War,</hi> Matth. 4. Eph. 2.2.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="486" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="98" facs="tcp:105695:63"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>486.</label> Thoſe in <hi>high dignities,</hi> like men upon <hi>perillous Precipices,</hi> are more <hi>pittyable,</hi> then <hi>envyable.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="487" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>487.</label> A <hi>Venice glaſs</hi> may, through <hi>carefull uſage,</hi> out laſt a piece of <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Plate</hi> unlook'd unto.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="488" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>488.</label> A <hi>ſmall Boate</hi> many times <hi>out-lives</hi> a Tempeſt, when an <hi>able Bottome</hi> makes an <hi>hole</hi> in the <hi>Sea.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="489" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>489.</label> 
                           <hi>Many ſmall</hi> Leakes may <hi>ſinck</hi> the Ship: and <hi>many ſmall</hi> Sins may <hi>drown</hi> the Soul in Perdition.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="460" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>460.</label> All <hi>carnall delights</hi> are Wine in the <hi>morning:</hi> Beere at <hi>noone,</hi> and Vinegar at <hi>night.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="491" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:105695:63"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>491.</label> 
                           <hi>Incendiaries</hi> want not <hi>VVoe,</hi> but <hi>VVit:</hi> When the Houſe is on fire, pray wher's the <hi>Bellowes?</hi> ſee <hi>Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm,</hi> 495.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="492" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>492.</label> No ſooner can any man get <hi>publique Approbation,</hi> but <hi>baſe</hi> Envy <hi>fly-blowes</hi> his <hi>Reputation.</hi> See to <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.1.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="493" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>493.</label> Every Foole can make a Foole; but he is <hi>cunning indeed,</hi> that can make a <hi>wiſe man.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="494" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>494.</label> Where the Heart is of a <hi>ſound Conſtitution</hi> within, there the life will be of a <hi>ſweet Complection</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="495" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>495.</label> 
                           <hi>Miſchief-mongers</hi> are like <hi>Fire-ſhips:</hi> while they <hi>martyr others</hi> they beſpeak but an <hi>hot</hi> bargain for <hi>themſelves.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="496" type="aphorism">
                        <pb n="100" facs="tcp:105695:64"/>
                        <p>
                           <label>496.</label> Unruly <hi>Rulers</hi> are like Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins, <hi>advanced</hi> one by one, to be <hi>thrown down</hi> by <hi>ſixes</hi> and <hi>ſeavens.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="497" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>497.</label> 
                           <hi>Covetous men</hi> are like the <hi>ſalt Sea;</hi> though they drink <hi>many Rivers,</hi> yet they are <hi>ſtill unſatified.</hi> See <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="498" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>498.</label> Wicked men ply their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as the <hi>Saylors</hi> their Pump, onely in a <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> and for <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>ſinking,</hi> ſee <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Jona.</hi> 1.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="499" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>499.</label> He that will not <hi>ſweat</hi> muſt <hi>weepe;</hi> he that will not <hi>labour,</hi> muſt be <hi>belaboured.</hi> See <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="500" type="aphorism">
                        <p>
                           <label>500.</label> A Wiſe man can learn <hi>farre more</hi> from a <hi>Foole,</hi> then a Foole can from a <hi>Wiſe Man,</hi> Prov. 24.30,31,32.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:64"/>
                  <head>Poſt-ſcript to the READERS.</head>
                  <l>THis Booke of late was out of Print (my Friends)</l>
                  <l>This half year laſt: but now, to make Amends.</l>
                  <l>I mended and (ſince that in hand I had it)</l>
                  <l>Three hundred Scripture Texts I ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added,</l>
                  <l>And more. But if no <hi>Captious Critick Brother,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do Carp thereat: I fear not any other.</l>
                  <l>For tis a Benefit and none Offence,</l>
                  <l>If ſome Quotations prove by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,</l>
                  <l>Or but <hi>Illuſtrate: A Judicious</hi> Mind,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:65"/>
                  <l>Therein ſhall (no ſmall) pleaſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Profit finde,</l>
                  <l>Then Chide me not: but rather giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me Thank,</l>
                  <l>For inter-ſcribing how to fill a Blank.</l>
                  <l>Expect if this cheap VVealth be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> refuſed,</l>
                  <l>A third Part, called, Little wit we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> uſed.</l>
                  <l>If God give Life and Leave: but thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> will be,</l>
                  <l>Scarce long before the next Feſtivity.</l>
                  <l>Mean while pick out, peruſe and practiſe well,</l>
                  <l>Such Truths, wherein moſt VVeight and VVorth do dwell:</l>
                  <l>Bleſſe God for what is beſt and moſt divine,</l>
                  <l>And ſo will I, and ſay the reſt are mine.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yet all are thine, and I once more in fine <hi>N. C.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Aug. 1 1656.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105695:65"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mercurius Deſideratus.</hi> THE WISE DOVE, OR TAME SERPENT; viz. The Conſcionable Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Compendiouſly chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteriſed in Proſe &amp; Verſe.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Nathanael Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Matth. 10.16.</bibl>
                     <p>Behold I ſend you forth as Sheep in the midſt of Wolves: be ye therefore prudent as Serpents, and ſincere as Doves.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Prudens <hi>Simplicitas</hi>
                     </l>
                     <bibl>—Martial.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>Printed in the Year, 1657.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="collection">
                  <pb n="104-105" facs="tcp:105695:66"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The wiſe Dove,</hi> or <hi>Tame Serpent.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Appy is the Mans whoſe Meditation, are pure, whoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes are <hi>ſavory,</hi> &amp; whoſe liſe is <hi>holy:</hi> who <hi>ſpeakes</hi> as he <hi>thinkes,</hi> &amp; <hi>doth</hi> as he <hi>ſpeakes.</hi> Who is a <hi>coward</hi> in Sin, but <hi>bold</hi> in Godlineſſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>1.</label> The man is bleſt, who dares be good</l>
                        <l>From Sur-face to the Center:</l>
                        <l>Who feels no Courage in his blood</l>
                        <l>On ſin to make Adventure.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>2.</label> Whom neither Sight can <hi>entice,</hi> nor Might <hi>enforce</hi> to do Evill: But he <hi>doth</hi> Good, and <hi>ſpeakes</hi> Truth even <hi>gratis,</hi> &amp; is peremptorily reſolved to be <hi>honeſt</hi> in ſpight of Earth and Hell.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>2.</label> Who can endure to be a Saint</l>
                        <l>Amids the Devills Traps:</l>
                        <l>Who is not honeſt by Conſtraint;</l>
                        <l>Nor ſpeakes Truth by meer Haps.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>3.</label> Whoſe Promiſes never out-run his Performances for want of <hi>Forecaſt,</hi> or <hi>after-Care.</hi> Whoſe Deſignes may be <hi>naked,</hi> &amp; yet not <hi>aſhamed.</hi> Who is not <hi>ſad</hi> at <hi>glad-tydings,</hi> nor coyns Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures to <hi>ſing</hi> his own party into a <hi>Fools-dream.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>3.</label> Who doth his Words with Deeds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</l>
                        <l>Whoſe Plots need no Diſguiſe;</l>
                        <l>Who at Good newes doth never Grieve,</l>
                        <l>Nor Lull himſelf with Lyes.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="aphorism">
                     <pb n="106-107" facs="tcp:105695:67"/>
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>4.</label> Who <hi>bends</hi> his Mind to <hi>ſhoote</hi> at Perfection, though the Arrowes of his Endeavour <hi>fall ſhort.</hi> Who loves not to <hi>plead</hi> Ignorance. Who <hi>conquers</hi> his Enemies by <hi>Patience,</hi> and <hi>murthers</hi> Injuries with Courteſies.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>4.</label> VVho would be better then he can:</l>
                        <l>who ſees no need of Blindneſſe.</l>
                        <l>VVho turnes his Foes Phyſician,</l>
                        <l>and kills Revenge with Kindneſſe.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>5.</label> Who deſires, to be both to GOD and Man a <hi>ſincere Nathanael,</hi> a <hi>true Church</hi>-Member, in Faith and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, without <hi>Malice,</hi> though not without <hi>Evill.</hi> Whoſe Humanity and Humility can never be <hi>Bankrupt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>5.</label> VVho is upright to God above,</l>
                        <l>Down right to Man below:</l>
                        <l>VVho ſtill payes All the debt of Love,</l>
                        <l>And yet the ſame doth Owe.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>6.</label> Whoſe <hi>well doing</hi> wearies out all his <hi>bad</hi> Pay-maſters. Who <hi>ſweates</hi> out the <hi>malignancy</hi> of Idleneſs. VVho is <hi>free hearted,</hi> and <hi>publique Spirited,</hi> and robs not Others of Himſelf.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>6.</label> VVho can do well ſpight of Ill-will;</l>
                        <l>WVho ſlayeth ſloth with Labour:</l>
                        <l>VVho lives as lent Himſelf until,</l>
                        <l>But given to his Neighbour.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="aphorism">
                     <pb n="108-109" facs="tcp:105695:68"/>
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>7.</label> Who never <hi>prides</hi> himſelf in <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary trifles,</hi> or <hi>future uncertainties.</hi> Who is not <hi>mad,</hi> but <hi>modeſt.</hi> Who ſcornes impudently to <hi>ſwagger</hi> with what his Maſter <hi>lent</hi> him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>7.</label> Who boaſteth not of Muck &amp; Rags;</l>
                        <l>Nor vaunteth of To morrow;</l>
                        <l>Whoſe Head is tame, who never brags</l>
                        <l>Of what he did but borrow.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>8.</label> Who furbuſhes his <hi>vertuous</hi> Habits by <hi>frequent</hi> Acts, and lets not his Time, nor Thoughts <hi>runne</hi> at <hi>waſt.</hi> Who thinkes himſelf leſſe then the <hi>least</hi> Mercy; and yet the <hi>whole</hi> world is not <hi>enough</hi> to fill his <hi>In-ſide.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>8.</label> VVho never lets his Graces ruſt,</l>
                        <l>Nor Time away be hurl'd;</l>
                        <l>VVho counts himſelf more vile then Duſt</l>
                        <l>yet better then the world.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>9.</label> Who doth not <hi>inviſibly</hi> wound his Brothers <hi>good name</hi> with Words <hi>worſe</hi> then Blows. Who is <hi>more</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable then <hi>most</hi> men <hi>deſire</hi> to be, and yet is <hi>angry</hi> with himſelf for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>no better.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>9.</label> Who whets not's Tongue upon his ſpleen</l>
                        <l>to cut an abſent Friend.</l>
                        <l>Who is as good as e're was ſeen;</l>
                        <l>And yet he ſtill doth mend,</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="aphorism">
                     <pb n="110-111" facs="tcp:105695:69"/>
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>10.</label> VVho whines not after his Neighbours <hi>glittering</hi> duſt; nor is <hi>toy-ſicke,</hi> like an <hi>bard to be pleaſed,</hi> Changeling, or <hi>incorrigible</hi> Self-humouriſt; who cares not ſo much for Liberty, as for Conſcience.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>10.</label> VVho never fondling like doth cry</l>
                        <l>For others Lands, or Houſe:</l>
                        <l>Who in his Chriſtian Liberty</l>
                        <l>Is Conſcientious.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>11.</label> VVho aſpires not to a <hi>faire</hi> Place by <hi>foule</hi> Play: who is not <hi>beggered</hi> by Plenty, nor made a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer</hi> through Proſperity: who ſtrives not to make the <hi>golden</hi> MINE a <hi>Poſſeſſive,</hi> nor <hi>poore</hi> Mens GETTINGS A <hi>Participle.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>11.</label> VVho growes not great without Gods</l>
                        <l>VVhom Riches cannot Pine:</l>
                        <l>VVho at vaſt Gold heaps lookes a-skew, leave</l>
                        <l>And, but in jeſt, ſayes, MINE.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>12.</label> VVho <hi>magnifies</hi> the Creator, and <hi>parvifies</hi> the Creatures: who ſets his <hi>Face</hi> towards the <hi>Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and by turning his <hi>backe</hi> upon <hi>tranſitory</hi> Delights, makes them <hi>ſhadow-like</hi> flock <hi>after</hi> him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>12.</label> Who feels the Brightnes of Gods love</l>
                        <l>Strike all Earths glory dimme:</l>
                        <l>Who mainly ſeekes the things Above,</l>
                        <l>And things below ſeeke Him.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="aphorism">
                     <pb n="112-113" facs="tcp:105695:70"/>
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>13.</label> Who is not <hi>cunning</hi> enough to deceive Himſelf, nor <hi>fooliſh</hi> enough to let others deceive him. Who is of a Serpentine <hi>prudence,</hi> leſt Another ſhould hurt <hi>Him,</hi> and of a Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine <hi>ſincerity,</hi> leſt He ſhould hurt <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>13</label> Who Chriſts true way of Life doth tread,</l>
                        <l>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting Grace with Art</l>
                        <l>VVho is a Serpent in his Head,</l>
                        <l>A Turtle in his Heart.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>14.</label> Whoſe Thoughts are like <hi>deepe,</hi> though <hi>cleare</hi> Waters, that may be ſeene <hi>into</hi> unto the <hi>middle,</hi> but not <hi>through</hi> to the <hi>bottome.</hi> Who is <hi>able</hi> to <hi>give,</hi> and <hi>willing</hi> to <hi>take</hi> good <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>14</label> Who is Profound, yet plain in ſpeech</l>
                        <l>To thoſe that can't diſcerne:</l>
                        <l>VVho is both wiſe enough to Teach,</l>
                        <l>And humble enough to Learn.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>15.</label> Who ſtudies not to cheat his own Soul, nor <hi>wearies</hi> himſelf with <hi>Frivolous Impertinencies,</hi> neglecting the <hi>one thing neceſſary.</hi> But being ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of his own <hi>nothingneſſe,</hi> eſteemes Chriſt <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>15</label> VVho is not ſtuft with fooliſh craft</l>
                        <l>His own ſoul to deſeate:</l>
                        <l>VVho is imperfect, but well graft,</l>
                        <l>In him who is Compleat.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="aphorism">
                     <pb n="114-115" facs="tcp:105695:71"/>
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>16.</label> VVho is <hi>wiſe</hi> to do Good, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> to do Miſchief has no <hi>Knowledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> VVho by his <hi>prudentiall</hi> Innocency <hi>befooles</hi> the <hi>profound</hi> Politician, and <hi>confutes</hi> the <hi>grand</hi> Impoſtor.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>16.</label> Who is in God a knowing man,</l>
                        <l>A very Child in evill:</l>
                        <l>Who ſilly-ſimple is, yet can</l>
                        <l>Out wit both Man and Devill.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>17.</label> VVho the <hi>older</hi> he growes, the <hi>newer</hi> he is daily; and the more <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit</hi> and <hi>crocked</hi> his Bodie is, the more <hi>ſtraight</hi> and <hi>upright</hi> is his Mind. VVho is both <hi>inferiour</hi> to the VVormes; and <hi>yet ſuperiour</hi> to the Angels.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>17</label> Who growes Young by Antiquity,</l>
                        <l>And lives when he is dead:</l>
                        <l>Who is but wormes-meat: yet more high</l>
                        <l>then Angels rears his Head.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="aphorism">
                     <div type="prose">
                        <p>
                           <label>18</label> VVho by Faith and Love <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſomes</hi> himſelf of all Self-intereſt: improves all he has for Gods <hi>glory,</hi> who turns all to <hi>his good.</hi> VVho, when we have ſeen &amp; heard the <hi>beſt</hi> of him, ſtill is far <hi>better</hi> within doores. Such a ones company <hi>Angels</hi> long for.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse">
                        <l>
                           <label>18.</label> Who reckons not himſelf his own;</l>
                        <l>But all things elſe are his:</l>
                        <l>Who lives as unto God well known,</l>
                        <l>That man is ripe for Bliſſe.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:105695:72"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript Quibuſlibet.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>FRiends, there was an errour, or <hi>Vice,</hi> in the Title of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication hereof, through the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteneſs of the Authour, from the Preſſe: And the <hi>late</hi> Advancement of the <hi>Patron.</hi> Wherefore tis thought good, to leave out the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Dedicatory</hi> to prevent <hi>a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> Miſtake</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="aphorism">
               <pb facs="tcp:105695:72"/>
               <p>
                  <label>1.</label> NEighbours, lay aſide Partiality, or the Booke, which you pleaſe, it will not hurt you unleſſe you will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="aphorism">
               <p>
                  <label>2.</label> That Reader who is over critical, I am ſure is Hypocriticall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="aphorism">
               <p>
                  <label>3.</label> 'The ſelf-ſame thing; if this man did it, it is too too Conceited; if another, tis Ingenious.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="aphorism">
               <p>
                  <label>4.</label> Nothing can be ſo bad, but ſome like it; nothing ſo good, but ſome diſlike it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="aphorism">
               <p>
                  <label>5.</label> Tis as hard to gratifie Every man, as to pleaſe ones Own fickle humour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="aphorism">
               <p>
                  <label>6.</label> VVhen I do well, I am envied: when ill, I am upbraided: Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, what ayle ye?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="aphorism">
               <pb facs="tcp:105695:73"/>
               <p>
                  <label>7.</label> Friends, Ye are many: But were ye more; do but agree among your ſelves, and I'le give you all ſatisfaction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="aphorism">
               <p>
                  <label>8.</label> True, My Garden has Weeds, as well as Hearbs; my Field Tares, as well as Wheat; my Buſh Prickles, as well as Roſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="aphorism">
               <p>
                  <label>9.</label> The Spider drawes deadly poyſon from the cordiall Slips; the Bee ſuckes honey from the heartleſſe Weed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="aphorism">
               <p>
                  <label>10.</label> My Apples have ſome ſoundneſs, licke not the rotten: My Sieve ſome Flower, eat not the Bran.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="aphorism">
               <p>
                  <label>11.</label> The ſincereſt Iſraelites may be, not without his Guilt, yet without his Guile.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="aphorism">
               <p>
                  <label>12.</label> The trueſt NATHANIEL may have his Errata, and the pureſt CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH its Imperfections here.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:105695:73"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edmund Calamie.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
